<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="grammar.xsl"?>
<ch id="01" t="Background and Historical Development">
  <sec t="Overview">
    <p><em>Styrian</em> is an alt-history Slavic language spoken across the eastern Alpine corridor between Czechia and Slovenia, roughly in what would otherwise be eastern Austria and Styria. In this timeline the Alpine Slavs of Carantania survive the medieval Frankish and later German political pressure and maintain a distinct community and language. Styrian is the sole member of an independent <em>Styrio-Slavic</em> branch, with early separation from the rest of Late Proto-Slavic and sustained contact with Bavarian German, Friulian, Hungarian, and neighboring West and South Slavic varieties.</p>
    <p>In English the people are called the <em>Straski</em>. In the language itself the ethnonym is [st Страски :t Strasky], the region is [st Стир :t Styr], and the language is called [st стирски :t styrsky] or in more formal register [st стириански :t styriansky].</p>
    <p>Synchronically, Styrian is highly analytic by Slavic standards, roughly at the same level of morphological reduction as Modern English. It preserves a recognizably Slavic core lexicon and the perfective versus imperfective aspect distinction, but it has:</p>
    <list>
      <item>a reduced two-case nominal system (nominative vs. oblique in the singular; plural is case-syncretic)</item>
      <item>a three-way grammatical gender system (masculine, feminine, neuter), with reduced but productive agreement</item>
      <item>only weak nominal inflection</item>
      <item>strongly reduced adjective agreement</item>
      <item>rigid reliance on word order, particles, and prepositions</item>
      <item>a simple proclitic definite article system</item>
      <item>a small but important set of irregular high-frequency verbs</item>
    </list>
    <p>Its most striking historical trait is an <em>early fixed initial stress</em>, which caused the weakening and later loss of unstressed vowels. This in turn eroded most inherited endings and pushed the language toward an isolating profile.</p>
    <p>The language has roughly 400,000 speakers in the modern era. It has a literary tradition from the 14th century onward and an established standard orthography in Cyrillic. Regional variation is modest; the main dialect division is between the highland western dialect and the lowland eastern dialect, which has somewhat more German loanwords.</p>
  </sec>

  <sec t="Historical Position">
    <p>Styrian can be imagined as descending from an Alpine Slavic continuum that split off after the major Common Slavic innovations but before the later convergence that defines the modern West and South Slavic groups. It therefore shares features with both zones without belonging cleanly to either.</p>
    <p>Its areal profile is roughly as follows. It is West-Slavic-like in preserving a relatively plain consonant system without later Balkan-style morphological complexity, and in retaining the inherited masculine, feminine, and neuter distinction rather than collapsing gender entirely. It is South-Slavic-like in retaining a productive aspectual opposition, an auxiliary-based past, and a pre-posed article system. It innovates beyond both through extreme reduction of unstressed syllables, strong reduction of case to a minimal nominative–oblique contrast in singular nouns, and the creation of a smaller, modernized agreement system: adjectives and adnominals distinguish masculine, feminine, neuter, and plural, while plural itself remains gender-neutral. The German influence further shaped purpose-clause strategy through a <code>za</code> + infinitive construction parallel to German <em>um zu</em>.</p>
    <p>The sustained German contact shaped the phonotactics and contributed loanwords in the domains of trade, administration, and material culture, but left the core grammar and most of the lexicon Slavic. A modest layer of Friulian and Latin loanwords entered through medieval ecclesiastical channels.</p>
  </sec>

  <sec t="Diachronic Development">
    <p>The history of Styrian falls into five periods. The phonological and grammatical changes form a coherent chain in which the initial stress innovation is the primary driver, and the subsequent analytical developments are its downstream consequences.</p>

    <sub t="Period I: Proto-Styrio-Slavic (c. 750-950 CE)">
      <p>The Alpine Slavs establish a distinct community in the eastern Alpine valleys. Their speech is still recognizably Late Common Slavic with a few early innovations.</p>
      <p><em>Fixed initial stress.</em> Contact with Bavarian German, which has a firmly initial stress, accelerates the leveling of the inherited mobile Proto-Slavic pitch-accent system. By around 900 CE, lexical stress has settled on the <em>first syllable</em> of all lexical words. Mobile patterns of the type <code>*golvá</code> are leveled to initial stress. Clitics and proclitics remain toneless. This single change is the motor that drives the entire later development.</p>
      <p><em>Denasalization of nasal vowels.</em> The Proto-Slavic nasal vowels denasalize early, as in most Slavic branches outside Polish. <code>*ę &gt; [st е :t e]</code> and <code>*ǫ &gt; [st у :t u]</code> in most positions. Examples: <code>*rǫka</code> &gt; [w ruka] "hand"; <code>*język[st ъ]</code> &gt; [st језик :t jezyk] &gt; <em>iezik</em> (borrowed/contact form later) and natively <code>*język[st ъ] &gt; [st език :t ezyk]</code> "language, tongue"; <code>*pęt[st ь]</code> &gt; [st пет :t pet] "five"; <code>*mǫž[st ь]</code> &gt; [st мужӑ :t mužă] "man, husband."</p>
      <p><em>Yat.</em> Proto-Slavic <code>*ě</code> (yat) is not immediately merged with <code>/e/</code> or <code>/i/</code>; it stays phonologically distinct during the early period, settling as <code>/æ/</code> and written [st ѣ :t æ] in the older orthographic tradition. This stage is reflected in the manuscript tradition and in 18th-century codified spelling. In the modern standard, however, the contrast has collapsed fully: <code>/æ/</code> has merged with <code>/e/</code>, and the letter ѣ is no longer written — all such forms are now spelled with [st е :t e]. Examples: <code>*rěka</code> &gt; historically <em>рѣка</em>, modern [w reka] "river"; <code>*sněg[st ъ]</code> &gt; historically <em>снѣгӑ</em>, modern [st снегӑ :t snehă] "snow"; <code>*lěs[st ъ]</code> &gt; historically <em>лѣсӑ</em>, modern [w les] "forest."</p>
      <p><em>Partial initial de-iotation.</em> Initial <code>/j/</code> is not lost across the board; it is reduced only in a closed class of high-frequency grammatical items where phonological attrition is greatest: <code>*jaz[st ъ]</code> &gt; [w az] "I"; <code>*j[st ь]mě</code> &gt; [st иеме :t yme] "name"; <code>*jest[st ь]</code> &gt; (reduced copula) → [w byt :i 3sg]. These are lexically specific reductions confined to the most grammaticalized items in the lexicon; outside this small set, initial <code>/j/</code> is retained in native vocabulary. The alphabet therefore preserves [st я :t ya] /ja/ and [st ю :t yu] /ju/ as standard iotated vowel letters, and uses [st й :t j] for medial and final /j/ glides. The letter [st ё :t io] is not used; the /jo/ sequence, found only in loanwords, is written [st йо :t jo].</p>
    </sub>

    <sub t="Period II: Early Styrian (c. 950-1200 CE)">
      <p>The critical structural changes of this period follow almost mechanically from the fixed initial stress of Period I.</p>
      <p><em>Jer merger to schwa.</em> The Proto-Slavic reduced vowels <code>*[st ъ]</code> (back jer) and <code>*[st ь]</code> (front jer) had already been weakening across Slavic. In Styrian, with stress firmly initial, the jers follow a split path depending on syllable position:</p>
      <list>
        <item><em>Strong jers</em> (in the first syllable, bearing initial stress, or immediately preceding a weak jer) vocalize: <code>*[st ь] &gt; [st е :t e]</code>; <code>*[st ъ] &gt; [st а :t a]</code> in most positions, but <code>*[st ъ] &gt; [st ӑ :t ă]</code> /ɐ/ (stressed) when the strong jer stands before a sonorant, liquid, or heavy consonant cluster. The letter [st ӑ :t ă] thus covers two phonetically distinct values: /ɐ/ under stress (from strong <code>*[st ъ]</code> in the stated environments) and /ə/ in unstressed position (from weak jers).</item>
        <item><em>Weak jers</em> (in all other positions) do not delete. Instead, the back jer [st ӑ] and the front jer [st ь] merge into a single undifferentiated schwa, written [st ӑ :t ă] /ə/ in the standard orthography. Both jers collapse to this one reduced vowel.</item>
      </list>
      <p>This is the key innovation that sets Styrian apart from other Slavic branches. Where Russian, Serbian, and Polish delete weak jers entirely, and where Bulgarian and Old Church Slavonic vocalize them to full vowels in certain environments, Styrian simply preserves them as a single weak schwa. The result is that all words that originally had a final jer retain a word-final [st ӑ :t ă] /ə/. During Period III this pattern extends by analogy to all consonant-final words (see below).</p>
      <p>Examples:</p>
      <tb>
        <r><c>Proto-Slavic</c><c>Styrian</c><c>Meaning</c></r>
        <r><c><code>*s[st ъ]n[st ъ]</code></c><c>[st сӑнӑ :t sănă]</c><c>sleep, dream (first ъ strong before sonorant → ӑ /ɐ/; final ъ weak → ӑ /ə/)</c></r>
        <r><c><code>*d[st ъ]n[st ь]</code></c><c>[st дӑнӑ :t dănă]</c><c>day (first ъ strong before sonorant → ӑ /ɐ/; final ь weak → ӑ /ə/)</c></r>
        <r><c><code>*l[st ь]v[st ъ]</code></c><c>[st левӑ :t levă]</c><c>lion (ь strong → е; final ӑ weak → ӑ)</c></r>
        <r><c><code>*p[st ь]s[st ъ]</code></c><c>[st песӑ :t pesă]</c><c>dog (ь strong → е; final ӑ weak → ӑ)</c></r>
        <r><c><code>*m[st ъ]gl[st а :t a]</code></c><c>[st мӑгла :t măhla]</c><c>fog, mist (ъ strong before liquid → ӑ /ɐ/; final -а is original, not jer)</c></r>
        <r><c><code>*s[st ъ]to</code></c><c>[st сто :t sto]</c><c>hundred (ӑ treated as enclitic, drops; no final jer)</c></r>
      </tb>
      <p><em>Loss of the dual.</em> The inherited dual number is lost, and its forms are absorbed into the plural, as in most Slavic branches.</p>
      <p><em>Beginning of palatal fossilization.</em> The old Slavic palatalization alternations stop being productive for new formations. New loans and coinages no longer trigger them. In the inherited lexicon, however, a small front-vowel-conditioned morphophonological residue remains, especially before inflectional -[st е :t e] and historical -[st і :t i]: <code>k &gt; c</code>, <code>x &gt; š</code>, <code>g &gt; ž</code>. This residue is preserved only in a closed lexical subclass rather than extending automatically to all velar-final stems; outside that set the alternations survive only as lexical residue in high-frequency items.</p>
      <p><em>Lenition of /g/.</em> Inherited <code>*g</code> shifts to a voiced glottal or pharyngeal fricative <code>/ɦ ~ h/</code>. This is preserved in the modern orthography as [st г :t h] (paralleling Ukrainian usage): [w hora] /ɦora/ "mountain." The letter [st х :t ħ] /x/ remains distinct.</p>
    </sub>

    <sub t="Period III: Middle Styrian (c. 1200-1500 CE)">
      <p><em>Completion of unstressed vowel reduction.</em> All post-tonic vowels continue to weaken and delete unless preserved by phonotactic necessity. The surviving vowel inventory in unstressed syllables is much smaller than the stressed inventory.</p>
      <list>
        <item><code>[st а :t a] &gt; ə &gt; Ø</code> in most post-tonic positions</item>
        <item><code>[st е :t e], [st о :t o] &gt; ə &gt; Ø</code> likewise</item>
        <item><code>[st і :t i], [st и :t y] &gt; ɪ &gt; Ø</code> in weak positions</item>
        <item><code>[st у :t u] &gt; ʊ &gt; Ø</code></item>
      </list>
      <p><em>No syllabic liquids.</em> Styrian does <em>not</em> develop syllabic <code>r</code> or <code>l</code>. When vowel reduction would otherwise strand a liquid or sonorant between consonants, a vowel is preserved in that position. Where the relevant syllable descended from a strong <code>*ъ</code> before a liquid or heavy cluster, the Period II back-jer rule already supplies a stressed ӑ: <code>*vъlkъ &gt; [st вӑлкӑ :t vălkă]</code> "wolf", <code>*krъstъ &gt; [st крӑстӑ :t krăstă]</code> "cross." Where the preserved vowel descends instead from a strong <code>*ь</code>, it surfaces as [st е :t e]: <code>*čьrnъ &gt; *černъ &gt; [st чернӑ :t černă]</code> "black" rather than **<code>чрнъ</code>.</p>
      <p>Because weak jers survive as [st ӑ :t ă] /ə/ rather than deleting, Styrian does not need to insert epenthetic а or е within consonant clusters the way Serbian, Czech, and Polish do. The surviving jer itself provides the syllabic nucleus at the word boundary. Consonant clusters that would have been illegal word-finally are resolved by syllabifying the schwa as the nucleus of the final syllable:</p>
      <list>
        <item><code>*dobr[st ъ]</code> → [w dobrə] (the weak final ӑ survives as schwa; /do.brə/; compare Serbian <em>dobar</em> with inserted -a-)</item>
        <item><code>*mogl[st ъ]</code> → [st моглӑ :t mohlă] (syllabified /moɦ.lə/; the cluster is resolved by the final schwa)</item>
        <item><code>*zemlja</code> → [w zema] (cluster <code>mlj</code> simplified; the final -а here is original, not a jer)</item>
        <item><code>*korl[st ь]</code> → [st кралӑ :t krală] "king" (after liquid metathesis; final ь weak → ӑ)</item>
      </list>
      <p>By the end of this period, the pattern of word-final [st ӑ :t ă] has extended by analogy to <em>all</em> consonant-final words, including those that never had a historical jer: [w hrad] /ɦradə/ "town", [w most] /mostə/ "bridge." The schwa is always unstressed and does not disturb the fixed initial stress. This final schwa drops before any inflectional suffix: [w dom] (sg.) → [w dom :i pl] (pl.).</p>
      <p><em>*kt development.</em> The Proto-Slavic cluster <code>*kt</code> develops in Styrian through velar weakening followed by coronal assimilation: <code>*kt &gt; *xt &gt; št</code>. This yields forms such as <code>*noktь &gt; *noxtь &gt; [st ноштӑ :t noštă]</code> "night." This development is independent of the Bulgarian and OCS outcome: Bulgarian reached <em>nošt</em> through palatalization of <code>*kt</code> before front vowel; Styrian reached the same surface cluster through <code>k &gt; x</code> weakening followed by <code>x &gt; š</code> assimilation before <code>t</code>, with no palatalization conditioning required. The patterns are parallel but not genealogically connected. The inherited affricates [st ц :t c] /ts/ and [st ч :t č] /tʃ/ are entirely unaffected by this development and remain in the phoneme inventory as normal consonants. Examples: <code>*noktь &gt; [st ноштӑ :t noštă]</code> "night" ([st шт :t št] from the independent <code>*kt</code> path); <code>*čьrnъ &gt; *černъ &gt; [st чернӑ :t černă]</code> "black" (strong ь → е, [st ч :t č] retained with liquid-support vowel); <code>*čьlovekъ &gt; [w čelovek]</code> "person" ([st ч :t č] retained; initial jer vocalized to [st е :t e] by the affricate–liquid constraint — the cluster [st чл :t čl]- is prohibited in Styrian onset position, so the Havlík-weak jer is treated as phonotactically strong; contrast West Slavic <em>člověk</em>); <code>*cvьtъ &gt; [st цветӑ :t cvetă]</code> "flower" (initial [st ц :t c] retained). Borrowings and proper names may be spelled with [st ц :t c] and [st ч :t č] directly.</p>
      <p><em>Case system reduction.</em> With final vowels gone or reduced to indistinction, the formerly distinct case endings have collapsed through heavy syncretism. By 1400, the inherited multi-case system has shrunk to a minimal residue: singular nouns preserve a two-way <em>nominative–oblique</em> contrast, while plural nouns show complete case syncretism. The nominative is the citation and subject form; the oblique is the general dependent form, used for direct objects and as the complement of all prepositions. Adjectives lose case agreement and most older inflectional distinctions, leaving only heavily eroded gender-number contrasts to be refunctionalized later. The primary burden of signalling grammatical relations shifts to word order, prepositions, and the light singular case contrast. A small number of frozen adverbs descend from older case forms ([st дома :t doma] "at home," [st ноште :t nošte] "at night"), but these are lexicalized remnants rather than a productive paradigm.</p>
      <p><em>Reduction and later restoration of grammatical gender.</em> Gender distinctions weaken substantially under unstressed-vowel reduction. In the late medieval language the old full adjective paradigm collapses, and masculine and feminine are only unevenly distinguished in the spoken koine. But the inherited three-way system never disappears entirely: feminine -[st а :t a] noun classes remain robust, neuters stay distinct, and masculine survives in consonant-final nouns, the article, and conservative participial usage. During the standardizing period the literary language regularizes these residues into a new reduced agreement paradigm with four slots: masculine singular, feminine singular, neuter singular, and plural. The result is not an archaic full Slavic adjective system, but a modern, phonologically eroded continuation of the inherited three genders.</p>
      <p><em>Grammaticalization of the definite article.</em> With the loss of the old pronominal adjective (definite) distinction between long and short adjective forms, a new definiteness marker develops from the unstressed clitic reflexes of the old distal demonstrative paradigm:</p>
      <list>
        <item><code>*t[st ъ]</code> (distal demonstrative, masculine nom. sg.) &gt; unstressed proclitic [w ta] / [st тӑ :t tă] (definite masculine singular article)</item>
        <item><code>*ta</code> (distal demonstrative, feminine nom. sg.) &gt; unstressed proclitic [w taf] / [st та :t ta] (definite feminine singular article)</item>
        <item><code>*to</code> (distal demonstrative, neuter nom. sg.) &gt; unstressed proclitic [w to] (definite neuter singular article)</item>
        <item><code>*ti</code> (distal demonstrative, plural) &gt; unstressed proclitic [w ti] (definite plural article, all genders)</item>
      </list>
      <p>The stressed demonstrative use of the distal forms developed separately into the modern demonstrative [st той :t toj], while the proximal demonstrative <code>*s[st ь]</code> remains as the stressed proximal [st сей :t sej] (see §Demonstratives). The unstressed proclitic forms of the distal demonstrative grammaticalized into the article system. The pattern of pre-positioned articles is reinforced by contact with German, where the article precedes the noun and similarly distinguishes grammatical gender.</p>
      <p><em>Stabilization of da-clause usage.</em> The inherited particle <code>*da</code> "so that, in order to" does not spread to all complement environments; it remains restricted to its original domains: purpose clauses and different-subject complements of volitional verbs. Same-subject complements of modal and volitional verbs continue to use the infinitive directly. A competing purpose strategy <code>за</code> + infinitive develops under German <em>um zu</em> influence as an additional same-subject purpose construction.</p>
      <p><em>Grammaticalization of the analytic past.</em> The old compound (perfect) tense built with the auxiliary <code>*jesm[st ь] + l-participle</code> displaces the aorist and imperfect, which disappear entirely. The l-participle becomes the clearest carrier of the restored singular gender contrast: masculine -[st лӑ :t lă], feminine -[st ла :t la], neuter -[st ло :t lo], alongside plural -[st лі :t li]. From this point, the modern past system uses four-form sets: a-class -[st алӑ :t ală] / -[st ала :t ala] / -[st ало :t alo] / -[st алі :t ali], and i-class -[st ілӑ :t ilă] / -[st іла :t ila] / -[st іло :t ilo] / -[st ілі :t ili].</p>
    </sub>

    <sub t="Period IV: Late Styrian (c. 1500-1700 CE)">
      <p><em>Rigidification of SVO order.</em> With case reduced to a light nominative–oblique contrast and articles developing, basic word order firms up as subject-verb-object. The minimal case distinction marks individual noun forms but does not encode enough information on its own to signal grammatical roles reliably in all environments; SVO position therefore becomes the primary organising principle. Scrambling survives only in marked, focused contexts.</p>
      <p><em>Conditional auxiliary.</em> The inherited conditional particle <code>*by</code> survives in reduced form as the invariant auxiliary [st би :t by], which takes an l-participle and expresses counterfactual or hypothetical meaning.</p>
      <p><em>Semigrammaticalization of `[w xotit]` and `[w možit]`.</em> The verbs "want" (from Proto-Slavic <code>*xъtěti</code>, cognate with Czech <em>chtít</em> and Slovenian <em>hoteti</em>) and "can" develop secondary functions as prospective future and predictive future auxiliaries respectively. This is reinforced by contact with the German <code>werden</code>-future, which is semantically more prospective than purely modal. The semantically shifted <code>*jьskati</code> root found in Macedonian <em>сака</em> did not reach this geographically distant Northwest Slavic area.</p>
      <p><em>Survival of a reduced present participle.</em> The inherited present active participle survives, but only in a leveled form. Sound change and analogical remodeling reduce the old paradigm to a highly simplified verbal adjective in -[st ачӑ :t ačă] / -[st ечӑ :t ečă]. Unlike the l-participle, which remains entrenched in the analytic past and preserves the restored singular gender contrast, the present participle stays morphologically much flatter and never rebuilds a rich paradigm.</p>
      <p><em>German and Friulian loanword layer.</em> Administrative vocabulary (related to the Styrian duchy and later provincial administration), crafts, and material culture show systematic German borrowings: [st шлосӑ :t šlosă] "castle" (&lt; Ger. <i>Schloss</i>), [st ритарӑ :t rytară] "knight" (&lt; Ger. <i>Ritter</i>), [st штал :t štal] "stable" (&lt; Ger. <i>Stall</i>), [st фарбат :t farbat] "to paint/color" (&lt; Ger. <i>färben</i>), [st гунт :t hunt] "dog (colloquial)" (&lt; Ger. <i>Hund</i>). Friulian and Italian contact gives words like [st мерштат :t merštat] "market, trade" (cf. It. <i>mercato</i>).</p>
      <p><em>Cluster simplification complete.</em> Three-consonant onsets are eliminated. The phonotactic profile reaches its modern shape.</p>
    </sub>

    <sub t="Period V: Modern Styrian (c. 1700-present)">
      <p>The standard written language is codified in the 18th century. The early orthographic conventions preserved the letter ѣ as an archaizing choice modeled on the older manuscript tradition; the distinction between [st і :t i] and [st и :t y] is likewise maintained. The modern reform abandons ѣ entirely in favour of е, reflecting the completed phonological merger, while retaining the і/и distinction as the one remaining historically grounded spelling contrast. The grammar stabilizes in its modern analytic form, including the standardized reduced agreement paradigm for adjectives, adnominals, and l-participles. In the verbal system, the reduced present participle remains primarily adjectival, though predicative uses with [w byt] develop into an optional marked progressive meaning "be in the middle of V-ing." Vocabulary expansion occurs mostly through compounding, calquing from German, and international Latin-Greek terms.</p>
    </sub>

    <sub t="Selected Lexical Developments">
      <p>The regular sound changes above yield forms such as the following:</p>
      <tb>
        <r><c>Proto-Slavic</c><c>Styrian</c><c>Meaning</c></r>
        <r><c><code>*ognь</code></c><c>[st огнӑ :t ohnă]</c><c>fire</c></r>
        <r><c><code>*myslь</code></c><c>[st мислӑ :t myslă]</c><c>thought</c></r>
        <r><c><code>*větrъ</code></c><c>[st ветрӑ :t vetră]</c><c>wind</c></r>
        <r><c><code>*ǫglь</code></c><c>[st углӑ :t uhlă]</c><c>coal</c></r>
        <r><c><code>*osmь</code></c><c>[st осмӑ :t osmă]</c><c>eight</c></r>
        <r><c><code>*zǫbъ</code></c><c>[st зубӑ :t zubă]</c><c>tooth</c></r>
        <r><c><code>*rǫka</code></c><c>[w ruka]</c><c>hand</c></r>
        <r><c><code>*pętь</code></c><c>[st пет :t pet]</c><c>five</c></r>
        <r><c><code>*ovьca</code></c><c>[st оуца :t ouca]</c><c>sheep</c></r>
        <r><c><code>*ovьsъ</code></c><c>[st оусӑ :t ousă]</c><c>oats</c></r>
        <r><c><code>*krъstъ</code></c><c>[st крӑстӑ :t krăstă]</c><c>cross</c></r>
        <r><c><code>*krъstiti</code></c><c>[st крӑстіт :t krăstit]</c><c>to baptize</c></r>
        <r><c><code>*vъlkъ</code></c><c>[st вӑлкӑ :t vălkă]</c><c>wolf</c></r>
      </tb>
    </sub>
  </sec>
</ch>
