<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="grammar.xsl"?>
<ch id="05" t="Syntax">
  <sec t="Basic Word Order">
    <p>Styrian prefers <em>SVO</em> order. Although singular nouns carry a nominative–oblique distinction, the case contrast alone cannot reliably signal grammatical roles in all environments; word order therefore remains the primary organizing signal. Subjects appear in nominative form before the verb; direct objects appear in oblique form after the verb.</p>
    <list>
      <item><ex>[w az] [w vydit :i 1sg] [w ta :i m.sg.obl] [w dom :i obl.sg]</ex> "I see the house" (subject [w az] nom; object [w ta :i m.sg.obl] [w dom :i obl.sg] obl)</item>
      <item><ex>[w taf] [w žena] [st вида :t vyda] [w ta :i m.sg.obl] [w čelovek :i obl.sg]</ex> "the woman sees the person" (subject nom; object obl)</item>
      <item><ex>[w ti] [st страски :t strasky] [w žyvat :i 3pl] [w ve] [w starə] [w hrad :i pl]</ex> "the Straski live in old towns" (plural nouns are case-syncretic)</item>
    </list>
    <p>Non-canonical orders occur with focused or topicalized constituents but require prosodic marking and are more restricted than in most Slavic languages.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec t="Noun Phrase Order">
    <p>The normal noun phrase order is:</p>
    <p><em>[Article/Demonstrative] [Possessive] [Noun] [Adjective]</em></p>
    <p>The article agrees with the gender and case of the head noun ([w ta] / [w ta :i m.sg.obl] masculine sg nom/obl, [w taf] / [w taf :i f.sg.obl] feminine sg nom/obl, [w to] / [w to :i n.sg.obl] neuter sg nom/obl, [w ti] plural), and adjectives and possessives agree in the same way.</p>
    <p>Examples — nominative noun phrases:</p>
    <list>
      <item><ex>[w ta] [w dom] [w dobrə :i m.sg]</ex> "the good house" (nom)</item>
      <item><ex>[w taf] [w knyha] [w dobrə :i f.sg]</ex> "the good book" (nom)</item>
      <item><ex>[w to] [w selo] [w dobrə :i n.sg]</ex> "the good village" (nom)</item>
      <item><ex>[w ta] [w moj :i m.sg] [w starə :i m.sg] [w dom]</ex> "my old house" (nom)</item>
      <item><ex>[w to] [w moj :i n.sg] [w starə :i n.sg] [w slovo]</ex> "my old word" (nom)</item>
      <item><ex>[w toj :i f.sg] [w knyha] [w holemə :i f.sg]</ex> "that big book" (nom)</item>
      <item><ex>[w ti] [w naš :i pl] [w dom :i pl] [w novə :i pl]</ex> "our new houses" (pl nom/obl)</item>
    </list>
    <p>Examples — oblique noun phrases:</p>
    <list>
      <item><ex>[w ta :i m.sg.obl] [w dom :i obl.sg] [w dobrə :i m.sg.obl]</ex> "the good house" (obl)</item>
      <item><ex>[w taf :i f.sg.obl] [w knyha :i obl.sg] [w dobrə :i f.sg.obl]</ex> "the good book" (obl)</item>
      <item><ex>[w toj :i f.sg.obl] [w knyha :i obl.sg] [w holemə :i f.sg.obl]</ex> "that big book" (obl)</item>
      <item><ex>[w ta :i m.sg.obl] [w moj :i m.sg.obl] [w starə :i m.sg.obl] [w dom :i obl.sg]</ex> "my old house" (obl)</item>
    </list>
    <p>High-frequency adjectives may optionally precede the noun for a more familiar or evaluative tone (see §Adjectives).</p>
  </sec>
  <sec t="Prepositions">
    <p>Prepositions govern the <em>oblique</em>. The language has a moderately rich set of prepositions, most inherited from Proto-Slavic.</p>
    <p><em>Core prepositions:</em></p>
    <tb>
      <r><c>Preposition</c><c>Meaning</c><c>Notes</c></r>
      <r><c>[w od]</c><c>of, from</c><c>also marks possession and origin</c></r>
      <r><c>[w do]</c><c>to, toward; for</c><c>also marks recipients and beneficiaries</c></r>
      <r><c>[w na]</c><c>on, at; onto</c><c>surface contact and targets</c></r>
      <r><c>[w ve]</c><c>in; into</c><c>takes epenthetic [st е :t e] before consonants</c></r>
      <r><c>[w za]</c><c>for, because of; behind</c><c>purpose and spatial "behind"</c></r>
      <r><c>[w yz]</c><c>out of, from within</c><c>motion from interior</c></r>
      <r><c>[st над :t nad]</c><c>over, above</c><c></c></r>
      <r><c>[st под :t pod]</c><c>under, below</c><c></c></r>
      <r><c>[w pred]</c><c>before, in front of</c><c>spatial and temporal</c></r>
      <r><c>[st пос :t pos]</c><c>after, behind</c><c>temporal and spatial (cf. [st после :t posle] adverb)</c></r>
      <r><c>[st при :t pry]</c><c>near, at, by</c><c>proximity</c></r>
      <r><c>[st без :t bez]</c><c>without</c><c></c></r>
      <r><c>[st мези :t mezy]</c><c>between</c><c></c></r>
      <r><c>[w so]</c><c>with</c><c></c></r>
      <r><c>[st преко :t preko]</c><c>across, over; through</c><c></c></r>
    </tb>
    <p>Old one-consonant prepositions take an epenthetic [st е :t e] before consonant-initial words. Thus [st в :t v] is normally realized and written as [w ve] before a consonant. All governed nouns appear in the oblique. In ordinary prepositional phrases the article is normally omitted; keeping it gives a marked, deictic, or contrastive reading:</p>
    <list>
      <item><ex>[w ve] [w hrad :i obl.sg]</ex> "in the town" (obl of [w hrad])</item>
      <item><ex>[w ve] [w dom :i obl.sg]</ex> "in the house" (obl of [w dom])</item>
      <item><ex>[w ve] [w hora :i obl.sg]</ex> "in the mountains" ([w hora :i obl.sg] is plural; plurals are case-syncretic)</item>
      <item><ex>[w na] [w reka :i obl.sg]</ex> "on the river" (obl of [w reka])</item>
      <item><ex>[w od] [w selo :i obl.sg]</ex> "from the village" (obl of [w selo])</item>
      <item><ex>[w so] [w čelovek :i obl.sg]</ex> "with the person" (obl of [w čelovek])</item>
      <item><ex>[w ve] [w ta :i m.sg.obl] [w hrad :i obl.sg]</ex> "in that particular town" (marked: oblique article retained under a preposition)</item>
    </list>
  </sec>
  <sec t="Possession">
    <p>Possession is shown either with a possessive determiner or analytically with [w od] followed by the oblique. The [w od]-construction also expresses source and origin. When a pronoun follows [w od], it takes its oblique form; when a full noun follows, it likewise takes the oblique. As elsewhere in prepositional phrases, the complement of [w od] is normally bare; an article here adds extra emphasis or points to a specially salient possessor.</p>
    <list>
      <item><ex>[w ta] [st мой :t moj] [w knyha]</ex> "my book" (possessive determiner, default)</item>
      <item><ex>[w taf] [w knyha] [w od] [w mene]</ex> "my book" (analytic, more emphatic or contrastive; [w mene] is oblique of [w az])</item>
      <item><ex>[w ta] [st негов :t nehov] [w dom]</ex> "his/her house"</item>
      <item><ex>[w ta] [w dom] [w od] [w žena :i obl.sg]</ex> "the woman's house" (analytic; [w žena :i obl.sg] is oblique of [w žena])</item>
      <item><ex>[w knyha] [w od] [st Марие :t Marye]</ex> "Maria's book" (proper noun in oblique)</item>
      <item><ex>[st иеме :t yme] [w od] [w čelovek :i obl.sg]</ex> "the person's name" (oblique of [w čelovek])</item>
    </list>
  </sec>
  <sec t="Clitic Pronouns: Inventory, Cluster, and Second-Position Rule">
    <p>Styrian has a set of short (clitic) pronoun forms covering accusative objects, dative objects, the reflexive, and the auxiliary forms of [w byt]. These elements cannot stand alone as full phonological words; they must attach to a host constituent. Their placement follows a <em>second-position (2P) rule</em>, shared with Slovenian and BCS and contrasting with the verb-adjacent preverbal clustering found in Bulgarian and Macedonian.</p>
    <sub t="Cross-Linguistic Background">
      <p>Styrian's clitic system belongs to the South Slavic 2P (second-position) type, shared with Slovenian and BCS, and stands in typological contrast to the preverbal clustering of Bulgarian and Macedonian. The cross-linguistic comparison is developed below because it motivates each structural choice in the Styrian canonical account.</p>
      <p><em>Slovenian.</em> The Slovenian clitic cluster occupies 2P — immediately after the first stressed constituent (XP₁) of the clause, whether subject, fronted adverb, wh-word, or complementizer. The internal hierarchy of the cluster is: <em>bi</em> (conditional) → AUX (<em>sem/si/je/smo/ste/so</em>) → refl (<em>se/si</em>) → DAT → ACC. In a positive compound tense the AUX is in the cluster: <em>Jaz sem mu dal knjigo</em> "I gave him the book" with cluster [<em>sem mu</em>]. The negative auxiliary forms <em>nisem/nisi/ni/nismo/niste/niso</em> occupy the same AUX slot (position 2) in the cluster, heading it in negative compound tenses: <em>Jaz nisem mu dal</em>, cluster [<em>nisem mu</em>]. The particle <em>ne</em> in simple-tense negation is proclitic to the finite verb and together with it forms a tonic unit [<em>ne</em> + V] that sits outside 2P; object clitics precede this unit.</p>
      <p><em>BCS.</em> The BCS cluster likewise follows the 2P rule with a six-position internal order: <em>li</em> (polar question particle) → <em>bi</em> (conditional) → AUX (<em>sam/si/je/smo/ste/su</em>) → refl (<em>se/si</em>) → DAT → ACC. The inclusion of <em>li</em> at position 1 is the chief structural difference from Slovenian. The negative auxiliary forms (<em>nisam/nisi/nije/nismo/niste/nisu</em>) likewise occupy position 2 in the cluster, heading it in negative compound tenses: <em>Ja nisam mu ga dao</em>, cluster [<em>nisam mu ga</em>]. Styrian shares the BCS pattern for all positions except position 1: Styrian [w li] is a post-verbal particle, not a clitic in the cluster, so the highest Styrian cluster position is [w by] (position 1 of the Styrian hierarchy), parallel to BCS position 2.</p>
      <p><em>Bulgarian and Macedonian.</em> These languages lack the 2P constraint entirely. Clitics cluster immediately before the finite verb, anchored to it rather than to the first constituent of the clause. In Bulgarian the preverbal cluster order is: <em>не</em> → AUX → <em>се</em> → DAT → ACC → V, so that <em>не</em> enters the cluster as its first member rather than standing outside it. In Macedonian the pattern is the same: <em>не му го давам</em> "I don't give it to him", <em>не му го давала</em> "she hadn't given it to him". This verb-adjacent preverbal system is characteristic of Balkan Slavic and is entirely absent from Styrian.</p>
      <p><em>Styrian.</em> Styrian aligns unambiguously with the Slovenian/BCS 2P model, consistent with its Carinthian areal affiliation. From Slovenian it inherits: 2P placement, the cluster-internal position of the negative auxiliary forms at position 2, and the non-membership of [w li] in the cluster. From neither BCS nor Slovenian does Styrian inherit the pro-drop parameter: Styrian requires an overt subject in all finite clauses. The consequence is that the subject's post-cluster displacement — invisible in pro-drop Slovenian or BCS because the subject can be null — is phonologically present in Styrian and constitutes one of the most characteristic surface patterns of the language. Wherever a 2P language would have a null subject after the cluster, Styrian has a pronounced overt pronoun.</p>
    </sub>
    <sub t="Clitic Inventory and Cluster Hierarchy">
      <p>The following elements participate in the clitic cluster, in fixed internal order:</p>
      <tb>
        <r><c>Position</c><c>Form(s)</c><c>Function</c></r>
        <r><c>1</c><c>[w by]</c><c>conditional particle (invariant)</c></r>
        <r><c>2</c><c>[w byt :i 1sg] [w byt :i 2sg] [w byt :i 3sg] [w byt :i 1pl] [w byt :i 2pl] [w byt :i 3pl] / [w byt.neg :i 1sg] [w byt.neg :i 2sg] [w byt.neg :i 3sg] [w byt.neg :i 1pl] [w byt.neg :i 2pl] [w byt.neg :i 3pl]</c><c>copular/auxiliary forms of [w byt] (positive / negative)</c></r>
        <r><c>3</c><c>[w se] / [w sy]</c><c>reflexive accusative / reflexive dative</c></r>
        <r><c>4</c><c>[w my] [w ty] [w mu] [w nam] [w vam] [w ym]</c><c>dative object (1sg 2sg 3sg 1pl 2pl 3pl)</c></r>
        <r><c>5</c><c>[w me] [w te] [w go] [w ykh]</c><c>accusative object (1sg 2sg 3sg 3pl)</c></r>
      </tb>
      <p>Two sets of forms are permanently <em>outside</em> the clitic cluster because they are phonologically tonic:</p>
      <tb>
        <r><c>Form(s)</c><c>Status</c><c>Function</c></r>
        <r><c>[w nas] [w vas]</c><c>tonic oblique pronouns</c><c>1pl and 2pl accusative objects; always tonic, never clitic</c></r>
      </tb>
      <p><em>Note on [w sy].</em> The form [w sy] serves as both the reflexive dative clitic (position 3, romanized <em>sy</em>) and the 2sg auxiliary (position 2, romanized <em>si</em>). Since Styrian requires an overt subject, the person of the subject always disambiguates: when the overt subject is 2sg [w ty], [w byt :i 2sg] is the auxiliary; with any other overt subject, [w sy] is the reflexive dative.</p>
      <p><em>нісем at position 2.</em> The fused negative forms arise from the fusion of proclitic [w ne] with the clitic auxiliary. Although the resulting form carries some stress on the [st ні- :t ni-] syllable, it occupies the same position 2 slot as its positive counterpart — it is the negative auxiliary heading the cluster, parallel to Slovenian <em>nisem</em> and BCS <em>nisam</em>. In practical terms, the positive and negative compound tenses have the same cluster structure: position 2 is always filled by an auxiliary form (positive or negative), followed by reflexive, dative, and accusative clitics at positions 3–5 (see §Canonical Cluster Templates below).</p>
    </sub>
    <sub t="Canonical Cluster Templates">
      <p>The following templates show the complete surface structure for each tense and mood, in both affirmative and negative. In each template: XP₁ = first stressed constituent; [cluster] = the clitic positions filled from left to right; S = overt required subject (shown only where displaced); V = the relevant verbal form(s).</p>
      <p><em>Simple tense (present/non-past) — positions 3–5 only:</em></p>
      <tb>
        <r><c>Polarity</c><c>Template</c></r>
        <r><c>affirmative</c><c>XP₁  [refl  DAT  ACC]  V-fin  ...</c></r>
        <r><c>negative</c><c>XP₁  [refl  DAT  ACC]  [w ne]-V-fin  ...</c></r>
      </tb>
      <p>In both rows, [w ne] is proclitic to V-fin and together they form a tonic unit outside the cluster. The cluster contains only positions 3–5.</p>
      <p><em>Compound past (perfect) — positions 2–5:</em></p>
      <tb>
        <r><c>Polarity</c><c>Template</c></r>
        <r><c>affirmative</c><c>XP₁  [AUX  refl  DAT  ACC]  V-part  ...</c></r>
        <r><c>negative</c><c>XP₁  [нісем/ніси/ні/нісме/ністе/нісу  refl  DAT  ACC]  V-part  ...</c></r>
      </tb>
      <p>In both polarities, position 2 of the cluster is occupied by an auxiliary form — positive in the affirmative, fused negative in the negative. Reflexive, dative, and accusative clitics follow at positions 3–5 in both cases. The participle stands at the end of the predicate.</p>
      <p><em>Pluperfect — positions 2–5 with double auxiliary:</em></p>
      <tb>
        <r><c>Polarity</c><c>Template</c></r>
        <r><c>affirmative</c><c>XP₁  [AUX  refl  DAT  ACC]  [w byt :i lptc.m]/[w byt :i lptc.pl]  V-part  ...</c></r>
        <r><c>negative</c><c>XP₁  [нісем/...  refl  DAT  ACC]  [w byt :i lptc.m]/[w byt :i lptc.pl]  V-part  ...</c></r>
      </tb>
      <p><em>Conditional — positions 1, 3–5 (no AUX at position 2):</em></p>
      <tb>
        <r><c>Polarity</c><c>Template</c></r>
        <r><c>affirmative</c><c>XP₁  [[w by]  refl  DAT  ACC]  V-part  ...</c></r>
        <r><c>negative</c><c>XP₁  [refl  DAT  ACC]  [w ne] [w by]  V-part  ...</c></r>
      </tb>
      <p>In the negative conditional, [st не би :t ne by] is a tonic unit; [w by] exits the cluster and joins [w ne] as part of this unit. Object and reflexive clitics remain at 2P before it.</p>
      <p><em>Non-subject fronting and the overt subject.</em> Whenever XP₁ is not the subject, the required overt subject is displaced to the position immediately after the cluster, before the finite verb. This applies in all tense/mood combinations:</p>
      <tb>
        <r><c>Tense</c><c>Surface order with fronted XP₁</c></r>
        <r><c>simple</c><c>XP₁  [cluster]  S  V-fin  ...</c></r>
        <r><c>compound (affirmative)</c><c>XP₁  [AUX cluster]  S  V-part  ...</c></r>
        <r><c>compound (negative)</c><c>XP₁  [нісем/... cluster]  S  V-part  ...</c></r>
        <r><c>conditional (affirmative)</c><c>XP₁  [[w by] cluster]  S  V-part  ...</c></r>
        <r><c>conditional (negative)</c><c>XP₁  [cluster]  S  [st не би :t ne by]  V-part  ...</c></r>
      </tb>
      <p>The surface sequence XP₁ → clitics → overt subject → verb is a uniquely visible property of Styrian among 2P Slavic languages, which are all pro-drop. It confirms that 2P is the organizing principle: the subject is displaced not because it is postverbal but because the cluster intervenes between XP₁ and the subject's normal pre-verbal position.</p>
    </sub>
    <sub t="The Second-Position Rule">
      <p>The clitic cluster attaches immediately after the <em>first stressed constituent</em> (XP₁) of the clause. In the default declarative clause XP₁ is the subject and the cluster follows it — an order superficially identical to a post-subject rule. The 2P nature of the constraint becomes visible when a non-subject constituent is fronted: the cluster follows the fronted element and the required overt subject is displaced after the cluster.</p>
      <list>
        <item><ex>[w az] [w mu] [w dat :i 1sg] [w taf] [w knyha].</ex> "I give him the book" — XP₁ = subject [w az]; cluster [[st му :t mu]] at 2P</item>
        <item><ex>[w utre :c] [w mu] [w az] [w dat :i 1sg] [w taf] [w knyha].</ex> "Tomorrow I give him the book" — XP₁ = fronted [w utre]; cluster [[st му :t mu]] at 2P; required subject [w az] displaced after cluster</item>
      </list>
    </sub>
    <sub t="Simple Tenses">
      <p>In simple (non-compound) tenses the cluster contains elements from positions 3–5 only (reflexive, dative, accusative). The cluster follows XP₁; the finite verb and remaining predicate follow.</p>
      <list>
        <item><ex>[w az] [w mu] [w dat :i 1sg] [w taf] [w knyha].</ex> "I give him the book"</item>
        <item><ex>[w ty] [w my] [w dat :i 2sg] [w voda].</ex> "you give me water"</item>
        <item><ex>[w ony] [w ym] [w prašat :i 3pl] [w to] [w slovo :i obl.sg].</ex> "they send them the message"</item>
        <item><ex>[w az] [w mu] [w go] [w dat :i 1sg].</ex> "I give it to him" — cluster [[st му го :t mu ho]]: DAT then ACC</item>
        <item><ex>[w taf] [w žena] [w te] [w vydit :i 3sg].</ex> "the woman sees you" — DP subject as XP₁; ACC clitic at 2P</item>
        <item><ex>[w on] [w se] [st мие :t mye].</ex> "he washes himself" — reflexive ACC clitic (position 3) alone in cluster</item>
        <item><ex>[w on] [w sy] [w kupit :i 3sg] [w novə] [w rob :i pl].</ex> "he buys himself new clothes" — reflexive DAT [w sy] (position 3) in cluster; subject is 3sg not 2sg, so this [w sy] is reflexive DAT, not auxiliary</item>
      </list>
      <p><em>Tonic нас and вас with co-occurring DAT clitic.</em> When the 1pl or 2pl is the accusative object, the tonic oblique form is used and it remains outside the cluster, following the finite verb. If there is also a dative clitic, that clitic occupies 2P normally and the tonic ACC form follows the verb:</p>
      <list>
        <item><ex>[w on] [w nam] [w dat :i 3sg] [w nas].</ex> "he gives us (to) us" — cluster [[st нам :t nam]] at 2P; tonic [w nas] post-verbal (this sentence illustrates the structural slot; pragmatically the more natural form is with a full NP object)</item>
        <item><ex>[w ty] [w ym] [w prašat :i 2sg] [w nas].</ex> "you send us to them" — cluster [[st им :t ym]] at 2P; tonic [w nas] post-verbal</item>
        <item><ex>[w az] [w mu] [st покажам :t pokažam] [w vas].</ex> "I show you (pl.) to him" — cluster [[st му :t mu]] at 2P; tonic [w vas] post-verbal</item>
      </list>
      <p><em>Fronted non-subject constituent:</em></p>
      <list>
        <item><ex>[w utre :c] [w mu] [w az] [w dat :i 1sg] [w taf] [w knyha].</ex> "Tomorrow I give him the book" — cluster after fronted adverb; subject displaced</item>
        <item><ex>[w taf :c] [w knyha] [w mu] [w az] [w dat :i 1sg].</ex> "The book I give to him" — topicalized object as XP₁</item>
      </list>
      <p>When the recipient is a full noun phrase rather than a pronoun, it is introduced by [w do] and no dative clitic appears: <ex>[w az] [w dat :i 1sg] [w taf] [w knyha :i obl.sg] [w do] [st Марие :t Marye]</ex> "I give the book to Maria."</p>
    </sub>
    <sub t="Compound Tenses">
      <p>In compound tenses the auxiliary form of [w byt] joins the cluster at position 2. The complete cluster follows XP₁; the l-participle stands at the end of the verb phrase.</p>
      <list>
        <item><ex>[w az] [w byt :i 1sg] [w mu] [w dat :i lptc.m] [w taf] [w knyha].</ex> "I gave him the book" — cluster [[st сем му :t sem mu]]</item>
        <item><ex>[w on] [w byt :i 3sg] [w ym] [w prašat :i lptc.m] [w to] [w slovo :i obl.sg].</ex> "he sent them the message" — cluster [[st е им :t e ym]]</item>
        <item><ex>[w az] [w byt :i 1sg] [w mu] [w go] [w dat :i lptc.m].</ex> "I gave it to him" — cluster [[st сем му го :t sem mu ho]]: AUX, then DAT, then ACC</item>
        <item><ex>[w on] [w byt :i 3sg] [w sy] [w kupit :i lptc.m] [w novə] [w rob :i pl].</ex> "he bought himself new clothes" — cluster [[st е си :t e sy]]; reflexive DAT at position 3</item>
        <item><ex>[w ty] [w byt :i 2sg] [w mu] [w go] [w dat :i lptc.m].</ex> "you gave it to him" — cluster [[st си му го :t si mu ho]]: AUX (2sg), then DAT, then ACC; the overt subject [w ty] identifies [w byt :i 2sg] as the auxiliary, not reflexive DAT</item>
        <item><ex>[w my] [w byt :i 1pl] [w ym] [w prašat :i lptc.pl] [w vas].</ex> "we sent you (pl.) to them" — cluster [[st сме им :t sme ym]]; tonic [w vas] post-participial</item>
      </list>
      <p><em>Fronted non-subject constituent:</em></p>
      <list>
        <item><ex>[w večer :c] [w byt :i 3sg] [w mu] [w on] [w dat :i lptc.m] [w taf] [w knyha].</ex> "Yesterday he gave him the book" — cluster [[st е му :t e mu]] at 2P after adverb; subject [w on] displaced after cluster</item>
        <item><ex>[w taf :c] [w knyha] [w byt :i 1sg] [w mu] [w az] [w dat :i lptc.m].</ex> "The book I had given to him" — topicalized object as XP₁; cluster [[st сем му :t sem mu]]; subject [w az] displaced</item>
      </list>
      <p>The conditional particle [w by] occupies position 1. In a plain conditional clause (no perfect auxiliary) the cluster is [[w by]] + any reflexive/DAT/ACC clitics:</p>
      <list>
        <item><ex>[w az] [w by] [w mu] [w dat :i lptc.m] [w taf] [w knyha].</ex> "I would give him the book" — cluster [[st би му :t by mu]]</item>
        <item><ex>[w on] [w by] [w mu] [w go] [w dat :i lptc.m].</ex> "he would give it to him" — cluster [[st би му го :t by mu ho]]: conditional, DAT, ACC</item>
        <item><ex>[w ty] [w by] [w se] [st умілӑ :t umilă].</ex> "you would wash yourself" — cluster [[st би се :t by se]]: conditional, reflexive ACC</item>
      </list>
      <p><em>Pluperfect and clitics.</em> The pluperfect uses a double-auxiliary construction (present AUX + l-participle of [w byt] + main l-participle; see §Pluperfect). The clitic AUX from position 2 heads the cluster in the usual way; both participles follow outside the cluster:</p>
      <list>
        <item><ex>[w az] [w byt :i 1sg] [w mu] [st билӑ :t bylă] [w dat :i lptc.m] [w taf] [w knyha].</ex> "I had given him the book" — cluster [[st сем му :t sem mu]]; then [st билӑ :t bylă] and main participle [w dat :i lptc.m]</item>
        <item><ex>[w ony] [w byt :i 3pl] [w ym] [st билі :t byli] [w prašat :i lptc.pl] [w to] [w slovo :i obl.sg].</ex> "they had sent them the message" — cluster [[st су им :t su ym]]</item>
        <item><ex>[st Пре :t Pre] [w dat :i 3sg] [w doit :i 3sg] [w on], [w az] [w byt :i 1sg] [w mu] [w go] [st билӑ :t bylă] [w dat :i lptc.m].</ex> "Before he arrived, I had given it to him" — cluster [[st сем му го :t sem mu ho]]</item>
      </list>
    </sub>
    <sub t="Negation and the Clitic Cluster">
      <p>The fundamental rule is: [w ne] is proclitic to the leftmost verbal element in the clause — the finite verb in simple tenses, or the conditional particle [w by] in the conditional. Together [w ne] and its host form a <em>tonic unit</em> that stands outside the 2P clitic cluster. Object and reflexive clitics (positions 3–5) remain at 2P before this tonic unit.</p>
      <p>The auxiliary [w byt] behaves consistently across positive and negative compound tenses: its forms always occupy position 2 in the cluster. In the negative, the fused forms [w byt.neg :i 1sg], [w byt.neg :i 2sg], [w byt.neg :i 3sg], [w byt.neg :i 1pl], [w byt.neg :i 2pl], [w byt.neg :i 3pl] — products of [w ne] + the clitic auxiliary — occupy that same position 2 slot, heading the cluster just as the positive forms do. Reflexive, dative, and accusative clitics follow at positions 3–5.</p>
      <p><em>Simple tense, negated — cluster [refl DAT ACC] before не-V:</em></p>
      <list>
        <item><ex>[w az] [w mu] [w ne] [w dat :i 1sg] [w taf] [w knyha].</ex> "I don't give him the book" — cluster [[st му :t mu]] at 2P; tonic [st не дам :t ne dam] follows</item>
        <item><ex>[w ty] [w my] [w ne] [w dat :i 2sg] [w voda].</ex> "you don't give me water"</item>
        <item><ex>[w az] [w se] [w ne] [st мием :t myem].</ex> "I don't wash myself" — reflexive ACC at 2P</item>
        <item><ex>[w az] [w mu] [w go] [w ne] [w dat :i 1sg].</ex> "I don't give it to him" — cluster [[st му го :t mu ho]]: DAT then ACC at 2P; tonic [st не дам :t ne dam] follows</item>
        <item><ex>[w ony] [w ym] [w ne] [w prašat :i 3pl] [w vas].</ex> "they don't send you (pl.) to them" — cluster [[st им :t ym]]; tonic [st не прашут :t ne prašut]; tonic [w vas] post-verbal</item>
      </list>
      <p><em>Compound tense (perfect), negated — cluster [нісем/etc. DAT ACC]:</em></p>
      <p>The negative parallels the affirmative: in <ex>[w az] [w byt :i 1sg] [w mu] [w dat :i lptc.m]</ex> the cluster is [[st сем му :t sem mu]], with AUX at position 2. In the negative, the fused AUX heads the cluster in the same slot: <ex>[w az] [w byt.neg :i 1sg] [w mu] [w dat :i lptc.m]</ex>, cluster [[st нісем му :t nisem mu]]:</p>
      <list>
        <item><ex>[w az] [w byt.neg :i 1sg] [w mu] [w dat :i lptc.m] [w taf] [w knyha].</ex> "I didn't give him the book" — cluster [[st нісем му :t nisem mu]]: neg-AUX at position 2, DAT at position 4</item>
        <item><ex>[w on] [w byt.neg :i 3sg] [w ym] [w prašat :i lptc.m] [w to] [w slovo :i obl.sg].</ex> "he did not send them the message" — cluster [[st ні им :t ni ym]]: neg-AUX then DAT</item>
        <item><ex>[w az] [w byt.neg :i 1sg] [w mu] [w go] [w dat :i lptc.m].</ex> "I didn't give it to him" — cluster [[st нісем му го :t nisem mu ho]]: neg-AUX at position 2, DAT at position 4, ACC at position 5</item>
        <item><ex>[w on] [w byt.neg :i 3sg] [w se] [st умілӑ :t umilă].</ex> "he didn't wash himself" — cluster [[st ні се :t ni se]]: neg-AUX then reflexive</item>
        <item><ex>[w ty] [w byt.neg :i 2sg] [w ydat :i lptc.m] [w tuka].</ex> "you didn't come here" — no object or reflexive clitics; cluster [[w byt.neg :i 2sg]] only</item>
        <item><ex>[w my] [w byt.neg :i 1pl] [w ym] [w dat :i lptc.pl] [w vas].</ex> "we didn't give you (pl.) to them" — cluster [[st нісме им :t nisme ym]]; tonic [w vas] post-participial</item>
      </list>
      <p><em>Pluperfect, negated — neg-AUX heads cluster, both participles follow:</em></p>
      <list>
        <item><ex>[w az] [w byt.neg :i 1sg] [w mu] [st билӑ :t bylă] [w dat :i lptc.m] [w taf] [w knyha].</ex> "I hadn't given him the book" — cluster [[st нісем му :t nisem mu]]; [st билӑ :t bylă] and main participle [w dat :i lptc.m] follow outside the cluster</item>
        <item><ex>[w ony] [w byt.neg :i 3pl] [w ym] [st билі :t byli] [w prašat :i lptc.pl] [w to] [w slovo :i obl.sg].</ex> "they hadn't sent them the message" — cluster [[st нісу им :t nisu ym]]</item>
      </list>
      <p><em>Conditional, negated — не би is a tonic unit; clitics remain at 2P before it:</em></p>
      <p>In the affirmative conditional, [w by] is at cluster position 1. In the negative, [w ne] attaches to [w by] and the combined [st не би :t ne by] is tonic. [w by] therefore exits the cluster; only object and reflexive clitics (positions 3–5) remain at 2P:</p>
      <list>
        <item><ex>[w az] [w mu] [w ne] [w by] [w dat :i lptc.m] [w taf] [w knyha].</ex> "I wouldn't give him the book" — cluster [[st му :t mu]]; tonic [st не би :t ne by] follows</item>
        <item><ex>[w on] [w mu] [w go] [w ne] [w by] [w dat :i lptc.m].</ex> "he wouldn't give it to him" — cluster [[st му го :t mu ho]]; tonic [st не би :t ne by]</item>
        <item><ex>[w ty] [w se] [w ne] [w by] [st умілӑ :t umilă].</ex> "you wouldn't wash yourself" — cluster [[st се :t se]]; tonic [st не би :t ne by]</item>
        <item><ex>[w on] [w ne] [w by] [w doit :i lptc.m] [w tuka].</ex> "he wouldn't come here" — no object clitics; cluster empty; [st не би :t ne by] immediately follows subject</item>
      </list>
      <p><em>Fronted non-subject, negated — neg-AUX heads cluster at 2P, then displaced overt subject:</em></p>
      <list>
        <item><ex>[w večer :c] [w byt.neg :i 3sg] [w mu] [w on] [w dat :i lptc.m] [w taf] [w knyha].</ex> "Yesterday he didn't give him the book" — XP₁ = [w večer]; cluster [[st ні му :t ni mu]] at 2P; required subject [w on] displaced after cluster</item>
        <item><ex>[w večer :c] [w byt.neg :i 3sg] [w mu] [w go] [w on] [w dat :i lptc.m].</ex> "Yesterday he didn't give it to him" — cluster [[st ні му го :t ni mu ho]] at 2P after fronted adverb; subject displaced</item>
        <item><ex>[w taf :c] [w knyha] [w byt.neg :i 1sg] [w mu] [w az] [w dat :i lptc.m].</ex> "The book I didn't give him" — topicalized object as XP₁; cluster [[st нісем му :t nisem mu]]; required subject [w az] displaced after cluster</item>
      </list>
      <p>When no object or reflexive clitics are present, the cluster consists of the negative auxiliary alone. The subject follows the cluster:</p>
      <list>
        <item><ex>[w on] [w byt.neg :i 3sg] [w doit :i lptc.m].</ex> "he hasn't arrived" — cluster [[w byt.neg :i 3sg]]; no other clitics</item>
        <item><ex>[w az] [w ne] [st знам :t znam].</ex> "I don't know" — simple tense; no clitics at 2P; [st не знам :t ne znam] immediately follows subject</item>
        <item><ex>[w večer :c] [w byt.neg :i 3sg] [w on] [w doit :i lptc.m].</ex> "Yesterday he didn't arrive" — XP₁ = [w večer]; cluster [[w byt.neg :i 3sg]]; subject [w on] follows cluster directly</item>
      </list>
      <p>This last example — fronted XP₁, cluster [[w byt.neg :i 3sg]], overt subject, participle — confirms that the subject is in its regular displaced post-cluster position. When the cluster holds only a single element (the neg-AUX) and no object clitics, the surface order XP₁ → neg-AUX → S is the expected output of 2P placement.</p>
    </sub>
    <sub t="Embedded Clauses">
      <p>The 2P rule applies within each clause independently. In subordinate clauses the complementizer or relativizer counts as XP₁ of that clause; the clitic cluster follows it. Because Styrian is non pro-drop, the required overt subject of the embedded clause is displaced after the cluster — a surface order with no parallel in pro-drop 2P languages.</p>
      <p><em>Declarative complements ([w dak]):</em></p>
      <list>
        <item><ex>[w az :c] [st знам :t znam] [w dak] [w byt :i 3sg] [w ty] [w on] [w dat :i lptc.m] [w taf] [w knyha].</ex> "I know that he gave you the book" — embedded XP₁ = [w dak]; cluster [[st е ти :t e ty]]; required subject [w on] follows</item>
        <item><ex>[w az :c] [st знам :t znam] [w dak] [w byt.neg :i 3sg] [w mu] [w on] [w dat :i lptc.m] [w taf] [w knyha].</ex> "I know that he didn't give him the book" — embedded XP₁ = [w dak]; cluster [[st ні му :t ni mu]] at 2P; required subject [w on] displaced after cluster</item>
      </list>
      <p><em>Different-subject [w dat :i 3sg]-complements:</em></p>
      <list>
        <item><ex>[w az :c] [w xotit :i 1sg] [w dat :i 3sg] [w byt :i 3sg] [w ty] [w on] [w dat :i lptc.m] [w taf] [w knyha].</ex> "I want him to give you the book" — embedded XP₁ = [w dat :i 3sg]; cluster [[st е ти :t e ty]]; subject [w on] follows</item>
      </list>
      <p><em>Relative clauses:</em> The subject relativizer [w ky] and the non-subject relativizer [w če] are each XP₁ of their clause. With [w ky] the relativized element is the subject gap, so no second overt subject is displaced. With [w če] the embedded subject is required and follows the cluster — a minimal pair that is diagnostically clear in Styrian precisely because the subject cannot be dropped:</p>
      <list>
        <item><ex>[w ta] [w čelovek] [w ky] [w byt :i 3sg] [w ty] [w dat :i lptc.m] [w taf] [w knyha]</ex> "the person who gave you the book" — [w ky] as XP₁; cluster [[st е ти :t e ty]]; subject gap</item>
        <item><ex>[w taf] [w knyha] [w če] [w byt :i 1sg] [w ty] [w az] [w dat :i lptc.m]</ex> "the book that I gave you" — [w če] as XP₁; cluster [[st сем ти :t sem ty]]; required overt subject [w az] displaced after cluster</item>
      </list>
      <p>Conditional and temporal embedded clauses follow the same principle:</p>
      <list>
        <item><ex>[w ako :c] [w byt :i 3sg] [w ty] [w on] [w dat :i lptc.m] [w taf] [w knyha], ...</ex> "If he gave you the book, ..." — [w ako] as XP₁; cluster [[st е ти :t e ty]]; subject [w on] follows</item>
      </list>
    </sub>
    <sub t="Clitic Climbing with Modal and Volitional Verbs">
      <p>When [w možit] or [w xotit] takes an infinitive complement (see §Modal and Volitional Verbs), object and reflexive clitics belonging semantically to the infinitival complement climb obligatorily to the 2P position of the matrix clause. The infinitive itself does not host clitics.</p>
      <list>
        <item><ex>[w az :c] [w te] [w xotit :i 1sg] [w vydit].</ex> "I want to see you." — ACC clitic [w te] climbed to matrix 2P</item>
        <item><ex>[w az :c] [w mu] [w možit :i 1sg] [w dat] [w taf] [w knyha].</ex> "I can give him the book."</item>
        <item><ex>[w az :c] [w te] [w ne] [w xotit :i 1sg] [w vydit].</ex> "I don't want to see you." — ACC clitic at 2P; [st не хочем :t ne xočem] tonic</item>
      </list>
      <p>Clitic climbing applies only to pronominal clitics. Full NP objects remain with the infinitive: <ex>[w az] [w xotit :i 1sg] [w vydit] [w ta] [st краль :t kral]</ex> "I want to see the king."</p>
    </sub>
    <sub t="Imperatives and Clitics">
      <p>In imperative clauses a special condition applies. The 2sg and 2pl imperatives have no overt subject: Styrian's non pro-drop requirement holds in declarative and indicative clauses because finite verb agreement alone cannot identify the referent in Styrian's reduced paradigm, but imperatives address an understood second-person participant and the language follows the widespread cross-linguistic pattern of allowing subject omission in the imperative even when it is otherwise prohibited. The imperative verb form itself therefore occupies the initial position of the clause and constitutes XP₁. Clitics follow it post-verbally, consistent with the 2P rule: the imperative is the first constituent, and the cluster immediately follows it.</p>
      <p><em>2sg imperative with clitics:</em></p>
      <list>
        <item><ex>[st Даі :t dai] [w mu] [w taf] [w knyha]!</ex> "Give him the book!" — cluster [[st му :t mu]] post-verbal, after imperative</item>
        <item><ex>[st Даі :t dai] [w mu] [w go]!</ex> "Give it to him!" — cluster [[st му го :t mu ho]]: DAT then ACC post-verbal</item>
        <item><ex>[st Покажи :t pokaži] [w my] [w go]!</ex> "Show it to me!" — cluster [[st ми го :t my ho]]</item>
        <item><ex>[st Умі :t umi] [w se]!</ex> "Wash yourself!" — reflexive ACC [w se] post-verbal</item>
        <item><ex>[st Піші :t piši] [w mu]!</ex> "Write to him!" — DAT clitic post-verbal</item>
      </list>
      <p><em>2pl imperative with clitics:</em></p>
      <list>
        <item><ex>[st Даіте :t dayte] [w ym] [w taf] [w knyha]!</ex> "Give them the book!" — cluster [[st им :t ym]] post-verbal</item>
        <item><ex>[st Покажіте :t pokažite] [w my] [w go]!</ex> "Show it to me!" — cluster [[st ми го :t my ho]]</item>
      </list>
      <p><em>Negative imperative.</em> The negative imperative uses [w ne] before the imperative form. Since [w ne] + the imperative form together constitute XP₁ (the only verbal constituent), clitics follow this tonic unit post-verbally:</p>
      <list>
        <item><ex>[w ne :c] [st даі :t dai] [w mu] [w go]!</ex> "Don't give it to him!" — [st не даі :t ne dai] tonic; cluster [[st му го :t mu ho]] follows</item>
        <item><ex>[w ne :c] [st умі :t umi] [w se]!</ex> "Don't wash yourself!" — [st не умі :t ne umi] tonic; [w se] follows</item>
        <item><ex>[w ne :c] [st пішіте :t pišite] [w my] [w to]!</ex> "Don't write that to me!" — cluster [[w my]] after [st не пішіте :t ne pišite]</item>
      </list>
      <p><em>1pl cohortative and 3rd-person нека constructions.</em> The 1pl cohortative ([w dat :i 3sg] + 1pl present) and the 3rd-person directive ([w neka] + 3sg/3pl present) are full finite clauses. The particle ([w dat :i 3sg] or [w neka]) counts as XP₁; the clitic cluster follows it at 2P; the required overt subject follows the cluster in the normal displaced-subject position:</p>
      <list>
        <item><ex>[w dat :i 3sg :c] [w byt :i 3sg] [w mu] [w on] [w dat :i lptc.m] [w taf] [w knyha]!</ex> "Let him give him the book!" — [w dat :i 3sg] as XP₁; cluster [[st е му :t e mu]] at 2P; subject [w on] displaced</item>
        <item><ex>[w neka :c] [w byt :i 3sg] [w ym] [w on] [w prašat :i lptc.m] [w to] [w slovo :i obl.sg].</ex> "Let him send them the message." — [w neka] as XP₁; cluster [[st е им :t e ym]]; subject [w on] displaced</item>
        <item><ex>[w dat :i 3sg :c] [w mu] [w my] [st дамe :t dame] [w taf] [w knyha]!</ex> "Let's give him the book!" — [w dat :i 3sg] as XP₁; cluster [[st му :t mu]] at 2P; subject [w my] displaced after cluster</item>
      </list>
    </sub>
  </sec>
  <sec t="Content Questions">
    <p>Content questions (also called wh-questions) ask about a specific open slot in the proposition. They place the interrogative constituent clause-initially. Since the interrogative counts as XP₁, any clitic cluster follows it in second position. If no clitic is present, the clause otherwise shows the ordinary sequence; if a clitic is present, the overt subject follows the cluster.</p>
    <tb>
      <r><c>Form</c><c>Function</c><c>Typical pattern</c></r>
      <r><c>[w koj]</c><c>"who"</c><c><em>[w koj] + V</em> (subject) or <em>P + [w koj] + (cluster) + S + V</em> (oblique)</c></r>
      <r><c>[w če]</c><c>"what"</c><c><em>[w če] + (cluster) + S + V</em></c></r>
      <r><c>[w kəde]</c><c>"where"</c><c><em>[w kəde] + (cluster) + S + V</em></c></r>
      <r><c>[w koga]</c><c>"when"</c><c><em>[w koga] + (cluster) + S + V</em></c></r>
      <r><c>[w zače]</c><c>"why"</c><c><em>[w zače] + (cluster) + S + V</em></c></r>
      <r><c>[w kol]</c><c>measure/degree interrogative: "how much, how many, how long, how + adjective/adverb"</c><c><em>[w kol] + noun / adjective / adverb</em></c></r>
    </tb>
    <p>The basic contrast is between subject questions, where the interrogative itself fills the subject slot, and non-subject questions, where any clitic cluster immediately follows the interrogative in second position and the overt subject follows the cluster.</p>
    <list>
      <item><ex>[w koj] [w pysat :i 3sg] [w taf] [w knyha]?</ex> "who is writing the book?" (subject question)</item>
      <item><ex>[w če] [w ty] [w pysat :i 2sg]?</ex> "what are you writing?" (object question)</item>
      <item><ex>[w kəde] [w ony] [w žyvat :i 3pl]?</ex> "where do they live?" (locative adjunct)</item>
      <item><ex>[w koga] [w on] [w doit :i 3sg]?</ex> "when will he come?" (temporal adjunct)</item>
      <item><ex>[w zače] [w byt.neg :i 2sg] [w ty] [w ydat :i lptc.m]?</ex> "why did you not go?" (causal adjunct) — XP₁ = [w zače]; cluster [[w byt.neg :i 2sg]]; displaced subject [w ty]</item>
      <item><ex>[w kol] [w voda] [w ymat :i 3sg]?</ex> "how much water is there?" (measure)</item>
    </list>
    <p>The degree interrogative [w kol] also combines with adjectives and adverbs to form degree questions equivalent to English "how + adjective/adverb". The pattern is <em>[w kol] + adjective/adverb + (S) + V</em>:</p>
    <list>
      <item><ex>[w kol] [w byt :i 3sg] [w holemə] [w ta] [w dom]?</ex> "how big is the house?"</item>
      <item><ex>[w kol] [st добре :t dobre] [w ty] [w pysat :i 2sg]?</ex> "how well do you write?"</item>
      <item><ex>[w kol] [st дуго :t duho] [w on] [w byt :i 3sg] [w ydat :i lptc.m]?</ex> "how long has he been gone?"</item>
    </list>
    <p>Styrian interrogatives do not themselves inflect for case. Prepositional complements are built analytically with prepositions fronted together with the interrogative; the preposition governs the oblique and stays with the interrogative rather than being stranded:</p>
    <list>
      <item><ex>[w do] [w koj] [w ty] [w dat :i 2sg] [w taf] [w knyha]?</ex> "to whom are you giving the book?"</item>
      <item><ex>[w so] [w če] [w ony] [w pysat :i 3pl]?</ex> "with what are they writing?"</item>
      <item><ex>[w od] [w koj] [w byt :i 3sg] [w taf] [w knyha]?</ex> "whose book is it?" (lit. "of whom is the book?")</item>
    </list>
    <p>Content questions do not use the polar particle [w li] (see §Polar Questions): the interrogative itself unambiguously marks the clause as a question, and the falling–rise intonation of the open slot signals which information is being sought.</p>
    <p>Several interrogative forms also serve elsewhere in the grammar: [w kəde] and [w koga] are also used as relative adverbs, while [w zače] can function as a causal conjunction "because". As in many analytic Balkan-style systems, the same surface forms connect direct questions, subordinate clauses, and relativization.</p>
    <p>These same interrogative stems also underlie the productive indefinite, negative, and universal series described in §Pronouns: [st некой :t nekoj] / [st никой :t nykoj] / [st всекой :t vsekoj], [st некӑде :t nekăde] / [st никӑде :t nykăde] / [st всекӑде :t vsekăde], [st некога :t nekoha] / [st никога :t nykoha] / [st всекога :t vsekoha]. The inherited [st всякӑ :t vsyakă] remains a special determiner meaning "each, every" rather than the regular free-standing universal pronoun.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec t="Polar Questions">
    <p>Polar questions – those inviting a yes or no answer – are formed by adding the enclitic particle [w li] to the declarative clause. Word order otherwise remains identical to a statement; [w li] is the sole formal marker of interrogative polarity, reinforced by characteristically rising sentence intonation.</p>
    <p><em>Neutral position.</em> In an unmarked polar question [w li] attaches immediately after the finite verb:</p>
    <list>
      <item><ex>[w on] [w byt :i 3sg] [w li] [w tuka]?</ex> "Is he here?"</item>
      <item><ex>[w ty] [w ymat :i 2sg] [w li] [w voda]?</ex> "Do you have water?"</item>
      <item><ex>[w ony] [w doit :i 3pl] [w li] [w utre]?</ex> "Are they coming tomorrow?"</item>
      <item><ex>[w on] [w byt :i 3sg] [st ли :t ly] [st виделӑ :t vydelă] [w taf] [w knyha]?</ex> "Has he seen the book?"</item>
    </list>
    <p><em>Focus-fronting construction.</em> If a constituent is contrastively focused, it moves to clause-initial position and [w li] immediately follows that focused constituent rather than the verb. The rest of the clause keeps its ordinary sequence:</p>
    <list>
      <item><ex>[w on] [w li] [w byt :i 3sg] [w tuka]?</ex> "Is it HE who is here?" (focused subject)</item>
      <item><ex>[w tuka] [w li] [w žyvat :i 3pl] [st страски :t strasky]?</ex> "Is it HERE that the Straski live?" (focused place)</item>
      <item><ex>[w utre] [w li] [w ony] [w doit :i 3pl]?</ex> "Is it TOMORROW that they are coming?" (focused time)</item>
    </list>
    <p>This focus-fronting construction differs from the neutral polar question only in the position of [w li] and implies a contrastive presupposition – the speaker assumes the proposition is true of some alternative and is asking whether the focused element, specifically, is the correct one.</p>
    <p><em>Negative polar questions.</em> Negation is expressed by [w ne] immediately before the verb, as in declarative clauses. With [w byt], the fused negative forms are used instead; [w li] then follows the verb or verb complex:</p>
    <list>
      <item><ex>[w on] [w byt.neg :i 3sg] [w li] [w tuka]?</ex> "Isn't he here?"</item>
      <item><ex>[w ty] [w ne] [w ymat :i 2sg] [w li] [w voda]?</ex> "Don't you have water?"</item>
      <item><ex>[w ony] [w ne] [w doit :i 3pl] [w li] [w utre]?</ex> "Aren't they coming tomorrow?"</item>
    </list>
    <p><em>Formal variant [w daly].</em> In more formal or literary registers, the compound form [w daly] – a fusion of [w dat :i 3sg] and [w li] – may appear as a clause-initial question particle. The remaining word order is fully declarative and no further occurrence of [w li] is required:</p>
    <list>
      <item><ex>[w daly :c] [w on] [w byt :i 3sg] [w tuka]?</ex> "Is he here?"</item>
      <item><ex>[w daly :c] [w ony] [w doit :i 3pl] [w utre]?</ex> "Are they coming tomorrow?"</item>
      <item><ex>[st Дали :t Daly] [w ty] [w ymat :i 2sg] [st повештӑ :t povaštă] [w voda]?</ex> "Do you have more water?"</item>
    </list>
    <p>The [w daly] variant is preferred in indirect yes/no questions embedded under verbs of asking and wondering (see §Subordinating Conjunctions for the corresponding declarative complement patterns): <ex>[w az] [w ne] [st знам :t znam] [w daly] [w ony] [w doit :i 3pl] [w utre].</ex> "I don't know whether they are coming tomorrow."</p>
    <p>Positive answers to polar questions are expressed with [w dat :i 3sg] "yes" and negative answers with [w ne] "no". Either can be reinforced by echoing the relevant verb form: [w dat :i 3sg], [w byt :i 3sg] "yes, (he is)" or [w ne], [w byt.neg :i 3sg] "no, (he isn't)".</p>
  </sec>
  <sec t="Relative Clauses">
    <p>Relative clauses are formed with a small contrastive series rather than a single invariant marker. The modern spoken standard distinguishes a subject relative [w ky], a general non-subject relative [w če], and specialized adverbial relatives such as [w kəde] "where" and [w koga] "when". This is still much leaner than an older Slavic case-marked paradigm, but it avoids overusing one form for every function.</p>
    <tb>
      <r><c>Form</c><c>Core use</c><c>Approximate equivalents</c></r>
      <r><c>[w ky]</c><c>subject of the relative clause</c><c>who, which, that; French <i>qui</i></c></r>
      <r><c>[w če]</c><c>direct object or generalized non-subject linker</c><c>that, which; French <i>que</i></c></r>
      <r><c>[w kəde]</c><c>place</c><c>where; Spanish <i>donde</i></c></r>
      <r><c>[w koga]</c><c>time</c><c>when</c></r>
      <r><c>[w od] [w ky] / [w od] [w če]</c><c>possessor, source, or other [w od]-phrase inside the relative clause</c><c>whose; of which; from which; French <i>dont</i></c></r>
    </tb>
    <p>The distinction is easiest to see in minimal contrasts:</p>
    <list>
      <item><ex>[w ta] [w čelovek] [w ky] [w pysat :i 3sg] [w knyha]</ex> "the person who is writing a book"</item>
      <item><ex>[w ta] [w dom] [w če] [w my] [w byt :i 1pl] [w kupit :i lptc.pl]</ex> "the house that we bought" ([w dom] is the antecedent and subject of the matrix; it is the implicit object inside the relative — oblique in that function, but unmarked as the head noun)</item>
      <item><ex>[w ta] [w hrad] [w kəde] [w žyvat :i 3pl] [st страски :t strasky]</ex> "the town where the Straski live"</item>
        <item><ex>[w ta] [st дӑнӑ :t dănă] [w koga] [w on] [w byt :i 3sg] [w doit :i lptc.m]</ex> "the day when he came"</item>
      <item><ex>[w ta] [w čelovek] [w od] [w ky] [st име :t yme] [w az] [w ne] [st знам :t znam]</ex> "the person whose name I do not know"</item>
    </list>
    <p>In word order, a relative clause follows its head noun directly. The relativizer occupies the left edge of the clause and counts as XP₁; any clitic cluster follows it in second position. If an overt embedded subject is present, it follows the cluster. Subject relatives therefore look like <em>[head noun] + [w ky] + (cluster) + V + ...</em>, while non-subject relatives look like <em>[head noun] + [w če] + (cluster) + S + V + ...</em> with the relativized element left as a gap inside the clause.</p>
    <list>
      <item><ex>[w taf] [w žena] [w ky] [st вида :t vyda] [w ta] [w dom]</ex> "the woman who sees the house"</item>
      <item><ex>[w taf] [w knyha] [w če] [w az] [w pysat :i 1sg]</ex> "the book that I am writing" (implied oblique object inside the relative)</item>
      <item><ex>[w ta] [w čelovek] [w do] [w ky] [w mu] [w az] [w dat :i 1sg] [w taf] [w knyha :i obl.sg]</ex> "the person to whom I give the book" — [w do] [w ky] as XP₁; cluster [[st му :t mu]]; required subject [w az] displaced after cluster</item>
    </list>
    <p>Styrian does not normally strand prepositions in relative clauses. If the relativized element is governed by a preposition, the preposition stays in front of the relativizer and governs its oblique: [w do] [w ky] "to whom", [w so] [w če] "with which", [w od] [w ky] "whose / of whom". Resumptive pronouns are likewise unnecessary in the standard language except insofar as ordinary dative clitics may still appear when demanded by the verb.</p>
    <p>In careful speech, [w ky] is preferred whenever the relativized element is the subject of the clause, while [w če] is preferred for direct objects and as a fallback non-subject linker.</p>
    <p>Colloquial speech may further generalize [w če] at the expense of other strategies, especially after inanimate antecedents, but the contrastive series above is the recommended standard and is the form used in this grammar.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec t="Free Relatives: The Article–Relativizer Construction">
    <p>Styrian has a productive construction in which a definite article stands without an overt head noun and is followed directly by a relative clause. The result is a <em>free relative</em> — a nominal phrase meaning "the one who…", "those who…", "that which…", or simply "what…". The construction draws on the full article system ([w ta] masculine sg, [w taf] feminine sg, [w to] neuter sg, [w ti] plural) and the established relativizer contrast ([w ky] subject, [w če] non-subject). It is the direct counterpart of Spanish <i>el que</i>, <i>la que</i>, <i>los que</i>, and, crucially, neuter <i>lo que</i>.</p>
    <tb>
      <r><c>Form</c><c>Relativizer</c><c>Meaning</c><c>Approximate equivalent</c></r>
      <r><c>[w ta] [w ky]</c><c>[w ky]</c><c>"the one who…" (subject gap, masculine)</c><c>Sp. <i>el que</i> (as subject)</c></r>
      <r><c>[w ta] [w če]</c><c>[w če]</c><c>"the one that/whom…" (non-subject gap, masculine)</c><c>Sp. <i>el que</i> (as object/oblique)</c></r>
      <r><c>[w taf] [w ky]</c><c>[w ky]</c><c>"the one who…" (subject gap, feminine)</c><c>Sp. <i>la que</i> (as subject)</c></r>
      <r><c>[w taf] [w če]</c><c>[w če]</c><c>"the one that/whom…" (non-subject gap, feminine)</c><c>Sp. <i>la que</i> (as object/oblique)</c></r>
      <r><c>[w to] [w če]</c><c>[w če]</c><c>"that which / what…" (neuter, propositional)</c><c>Sp. <i>lo que</i></c></r>
      <r><c>[w ti] [w ky]</c><c>[w ky]</c><c>"those who…" (subject gap, plural)</c><c>Sp. <i>los que</i> / <i>las que</i> (as subject)</c></r>
      <r><c>[w ti] [w če]</c><c>[w če]</c><c>"those that/whom…" (non-subject gap, plural)</c><c>Sp. <i>los que</i> / <i>las que</i> (as object/oblique)</c></r>
    </tb>
    <p>The article inflects for case in the ordinary way: when the free-relative phrase occupies an oblique slot (direct object or prepositional complement), the article takes its oblique form ([w ta :i m.sg.obl] [w ky] "the one whom…", [w taf :i f.sg.obl] [w ky] "the woman whom…"); when it occupies a nominative slot, the nominative form is used. A governing preposition simply precedes the article-relativizer unit without contracting with it. The internal clause follows the ordinary 2P rule: the relativizer counts as XP₁ and any clitic cluster follows immediately, displacing the overt subject as usual.</p>

    <sub t="Singular Personal Free Relatives">
      <p>[w ta :c] [w ky] and [w taf] [w ky] introduce free relatives in which the missing element is the <em>subject</em> of the embedded clause. The masculine and feminine articles now make the referent's grammatical gender overt. Because [w ky] is itself the subject gap, no second subject appears inside the relative clause:</p>
      <list>
        <item><ex>[w ta] [w ky] [w pysat :i 3sg] [w taf] [w knyha] [w byt :i 3sg] [w moj :i m.sg] [w pryyatel]</ex> "the man who is writing the book is my friend"</item>
        <item><ex>[w taf] [w ky] [w pysat :i 3sg] [w taf] [w knyha] [w byt :i 3sg] [w moj :i f.sg] [st приятелица :t pryyatelica]</ex> "the woman who is writing the book is my female friend"</item>
        <item><ex>[w ta] [w ky] [w byt :i 3sg] [st рано :t rano] [w doit :i lptc.m] [st ке :t ke] [w doit] [st пре :t pre]</ex> "the one who arrived early will come first"</item>
        <item><ex>[w az] [w vydit :i 1sg] [w ta] [w ky] [w te] [st шта :t šta]</ex> "I see the one who is looking for you"</item>
      </list>
      <p>[w ta :c] [w če] and [w taf] [w če] introduce free relatives in which the missing element is a <em>non-subject</em> — typically a direct object or a prepositional complement. The required overt subject follows the clitic cluster in the standard displaced-subject position:</p>
      <list>
        <item><ex>[w ta] [w če] [w az] [w xotit :i 1sg] [w byt :i 3sg] [st скапӑ :t skapă]</ex> "the one that I want is expensive" (missing object inside relative)</item>
        <item><ex>[w taf] [w če] [w az] [st шуком :t šukom] [w byt :i 3sg] [st умна :t umna]</ex> "the woman whom I am looking for is clever"</item>
        <item><ex>[w ta] [w če] [w ty] [w my] [st дадеш :t dadeš] [st ке :t ke] [w byt] [st добро :t dobro]</ex> "what(ever) you give me will be fine" (the free relative as subject of main clause)</item>
        <item><ex>[w on] [w byt :i 3sg] [w ta] [w če] [w az] [st шуком :t šukom]</ex> "he is the one I was looking for"</item>
      </list>
      <p>The contrast between [w ta] / [w taf] + [w ky] and [w ta] / [w taf] + [w če] tracks the same subject/non-subject distinction that governs headed relative clauses. The article contributes gender and number; the relativizer contributes the syntactic role.</p>
    </sub>

    <sub t="Neuter Singular: то че (the lo que equivalent)">
      <p>The neuter free relative [w to] [w če] is the most distinctive member of the series. Rather than referring to a specific countable entity, it nominalizes an entire propositional content — an action, a state of affairs, or an abstract concept. Its meaning corresponds closely to English "what" in clauses like "what you said" or "what happened", and to Spanish neuter <i>lo que</i>. The choice of neuter article [w to] marks the absence of a concrete, gender-bearing antecedent: the construction presents the content of the clause as an undifferentiated proposition.</p>
      <p><em>As subject of the main clause:</em></p>
      <list>
        <item><ex>[w to] [w če] [w on] [st каже :t kaže] [w byt :i 3sg] [st вистина :t vystyna]</ex> "what he says is true"</item>
        <item><ex>[w to] [w če] [w byt :i 1pl] [w napravit :i lptc.pl] [w byt :i 3sg] [st доволно :t dovolno]</ex> "what we did is enough"</item>
        <item><ex>[w to] [w če] [w me] [st мучи :t muči] [w byt :i 3sg] [w ta] [st тишина :t tyšyna]</ex> "what troubles me is the silence"</item>
      </list>
      <p><em>As direct object of the main clause:</em></p>
      <list>
        <item><ex>[w az] [st знам :t znam] [w to] [w če] [w ty] [w xotit :i 2sg]</ex> "I know what you want"</item>
        <item><ex>[w on] [w byt :i 3sg] [st рекалӑ :t rekală] [w to] [w če] [w byt :i 3sg] [st мислілӑ :t myslilă]</ex> "he said what he thought"</item>
        <item><ex>[w az] [w ne] [st разумем :t razumem] [w to] [w če] [w ty] [w pysat :i 2sg]</ex> "I don't understand what you are writing"</item>
      </list>
      <p><em>As complement of a preposition:</em></p>
      <list>
        <item><ex>[w az] [st мислем :t myslem] [w za] [w to] [w če] [w on] [w byt :i 3sg] [st рекалӑ :t rekală]</ex> "I am thinking about what he said"</item>
        <item><ex>[w my] [w byt :i 1pl] [st доволні :t dovolni] [w so] [w to] [w če] [w ymat :i 1pl]</ex> "we are content with what we have"</item>
        <item><ex>[w on] [st плаже :t plaže] [w za] [w to] [w če] [w byt :i 3sg] [st изгубілӑ :t yzhubilă]</ex> "he is paying for what he lost"</item>
      </list>
      <p><em>In predicate-nominal (pseudo-cleft) constructions:</em></p>
      <list>
        <item><ex>[w to] [w če] [w az] [w xotit :i 1sg] [w byt :i 3sg] [st мир :t myr]</ex> "what I want is peace"</item>
        <item><ex>[w to] [w če] [st она :t ona] [w ne] [st разуме :t razume] [w byt :i 3sg] [w zače] [w az] [st молчем :t molčem]</ex> "what she does not understand is why I am silent"</item>
      </list>
      <p>In all these uses the internal clause follows the 2P rule with [w to] [w če] as the frame, the relativizer [w če] counting as XP₁: any clitics follow [w če] in second position, and the overt subject of the embedded clause is displaced after the cluster in the usual fashion.</p>
      <p><em>Clitic order inside то че clauses (compound tense example):</em></p>
      <list>
        <item><ex>[w to] [w če] [w byt :i 3sg] [w ty] [w on] [st рекалӑ :t rekală]</ex> "what he said to you" — [w če] as XP₁; cluster [[st е ти :t e ty]]; displaced subject [w on]</item>
        <item><ex>[w to] [w če] [w mu] [w go] [w az] [w dat :i 1sg]</ex> "what I give him" — cluster [[st му го :t mu ho]]; displaced subject [w az]</item>
      </list>
      <p>[w to :c] [w če] is not available when the embedded clause identifies a specific person or concrete gendered referent: for those contexts the masculine and feminine forms [w ta] / [w taf] + [w ky] or [w če] are used instead. The neuter construction strictly signals propositional or abstract content.</p>
    </sub>

    <sub t="Plural: ти ки and ти че">
      <p>The plural free relative uses [w ti] — the same invariant plural article used for definite noun phrases — and applies to groups of persons or things. The subject/non-subject contrast is preserved in the relativizer choice:</p>
      <list>
        <item><ex>[w ti] [w ky] [w byt :i 3pl] [w doit :i lptc.pl] [w byt :i 3sg] [st добродошлі :t dobrodošli]</ex> "those who came are welcome" (subject gap)</item>
        <item><ex>[w ti] [w ky] [st хочет :t xočet] [w dat :i 3sg] [st помагут :t pomagut], [w neka] [w byt :i 3pl] [st слободні :t slobodni]</ex> "those who wish to help, let them be free to do so"</item>
        <item><ex>[w ti] [w če] [w az] [st шуком :t šukom] [w byt.neg :i 3pl] [w tuka]</ex> "those that I was looking for are not here" (non-subject gap)</item>
        <item><ex>[w on] [w byt :i 3sg] [w dat :i lptc.m] [w do] [w ti] [w ky] [w ymat] [st нужда :t nužda]</ex> "he gave (it) to those who are in need"</item>
      </list>
    </sub>

    <sub t="Free Relatives as Subjects, Objects, and Prepositional Complements">
      <p>In all its forms the article–relativizer construction occupies any nominal slot in the main clause. When it is the subject or predicate nominal the article takes its nominative form; when it is a direct object or prepositional complement the article takes its oblique form. A governing preposition simply precedes the whole unit and the relativizer's complement clause follows:</p>
      <list>
        <item><em>Subject (nom):</em> <ex>[w ta] [w ky] [st рано :t rano] [w doit] [st ке :t ke] [st наіде :t naide] [w dom] [st отворенӑ :t otvorenă]</ex> "the one who comes early will find the house open"</item>
        <item><em>Direct object (obl):</em> <ex>[w az] [w vydit :i 1sg] [w ta :i m.sg.obl] [w ky] [w byt :i 3sg] [w ydat :i lptc.m] [st напред :t napred]</ex> "I see the one who went ahead"</item>
        <item><em>Prepositional complement (obl):</em> <ex>[w az] [st говором :t hovorem] [w do] [w ta :i m.sg.obl] [w ky] [w byt :i 3sg] [w tuka]</ex> "I speak to the one who is here"</item>
        <item><em>Prepositional complement, neuter (obl):</em> <ex>[w az] [w byt :i 1sg] [st горд :t hord] [w od] [w to :i n.sg.obl] [w če] [w byt :i 1pl] [w napravit :i lptc.pl]</ex> "I am proud of what we have done"</item>
      </list>
    </sub>

    <sub t="Generic and Universal Readings">
      <p>When context is generic or the speaker asserts something true of any member of the described class, the article–relativizer construction shades into a universal or conditional reading, equivalent to English "whoever", "whatever", "those who (in general)". The form is identical; context, tense, and the modal or generic frame of the main clause supply the universal force:</p>
      <list>
        <item><ex>[w ta] [w ky] [st сее :t see] [st ке :t ke] [st жнее :t žnee]</ex> "whoever sows will reap" (proverbial; lit. "the one who sows will reap")</item>
        <item><ex>[w to] [w če] [w byt :i 3sg] [st направено :t napraveno] [w možit :i 3sg] [w dat :i 3sg] [w se] [st поправи :t popravi]</ex> "whatever has been done can be undone"</item>
        <item><ex>[w ti] [w ky] [st пишут :t pyšut] [w more :i pl] [w dat :i 3sg] [st читут :t čytut]</ex> "those who write must read"</item>
      </list>
      <p>Explicit universal and negative pronouns ([st всекой :t vsekoj] "everyone", [st никой :t nykoj] "no one"; see §Pronouns) are available when the universal reading needs to be unambiguous. The article–relativizer construction is neutral between "the specific one who…" and "whoever…", and speakers use context to resolve the ambiguity. In conditional protases the universal reading is strongly preferred.</p>
    </sub>

    <sub t="Diachronic Note">
      <p>The construction is the natural outcome of Styrian's loss of relative pronoun declension. Older Slavic relative-clause systems built a full paradigm of case-marked relatives from the pronominal stem <i>*jь-, ja-, je-</i>; Styrian levelled this paradigm to the two invariant forms [w ky] and [w če] (see §Relative Clauses). The non-subject form reflects later reduction in a very high-frequency grammatical item, yielding the short modern standard [w če]. Once the relative pronoun lost case inflection, the determiner force had to be carried by the article. The article–relativizer unit that results is thus a grammaticalized reflex of the older <i>[demonstrative + relative pronoun]</i> sequence, now reanalysed as a unified nominal head. The neuter [w to] [w če] is particularly revealing: it preserves the old neuter pronominal form <i>*to</i> not as a head noun but as a grammatical marker of propositional content, filling the same semantic role as Spanish <i>lo</i> or French <i>ce que</i>.</p>
    </sub>
  </sec>

  <sec t="Subordinating Conjunctions">
    <p>Styrian has a range of subordinating conjunctions for different clause types:</p>
    <tb>
      <r><c>Conjunction</c><c>Meaning</c><c>Use</c></r>
      <r><c>[w dat :i 3sg]</c><c>in order to; (for different-subject complements)</c><c>purpose clauses; different-subject complements of volitional verbs</c></r>
      <r><c>[w za] + inf.</c><c>in order to</c><c>purpose / final clauses (same subject; competing with [w dat :i 3sg])</c></r>
      <r><c>[w dak]</c><c>that</c><c>declarative complement clauses</c></r>
      <r><c>[w ako]</c><c>if</c><c>conditional clauses</c></r>
      <r><c>[w koga]</c><c>when</c><c>temporal clauses</c></r>
      <r><c>[w zače]</c><c>because</c><c>causal clauses</c></r>
      <r><c>[st хот :t ħot]</c><c>although, even though</c><c>concessive clauses</c></r>
      <r><c>[w pred] [w dat :i 3sg]</c><c>before</c><c>temporal (lit. "before that")</c></r>
      <r><c>[st пос :t pos] [w dat :i 3sg]</c><c>after</c><c>temporal (lit. "after that")</c></r>
      <r><c>[w do]-[w dak]</c><c>until</c><c>temporal</c></r>
      <r><c>[st одка :t odka]</c><c>since (temporal)</c><c>from <code>*ot[st ъ] + k[st ъ]da</code></c></r>
    </tb>
    <sub t="Modal and Volitional Verbs: Infinitive as Primary Complement">
      <p>Modal verbs ([w možit] "can") and volitional verbs ([w xotit] "want") take the <em>infinitive directly</em> as their primary complement. No conjunction or particle intervenes. This is the basic pattern and holds regardless of whether the construction carries present, prospective, or future meaning:</p>
      <list>
        <item><ex>[w az] [w xotit :i 1sg] [w pysat]</ex> "I want to write" ([w xotit] + infinitive)</item>
        <item><ex>[w my] [w možit :i 1pl] [w doit]</ex> "we can come" ([w možit] + infinitive)</item>
        <item><ex>[w on] [w xotit :i 3sg] [w vydit] [w ta] [st краль :t kral]</ex> "he wants to see the king"</item>
      </list>
      <p>The infinitive is the default complement pattern and is the expected form after all modal and volitional verbs when subject and embedded predicate share the same subject.</p>
    </sub>
    <sub t="Да-Clauses: Purpose and Different-Subject Complements">
      <p>The conjunction [w dat :i 3sg] is restricted to two environments: (1) <em>purpose clauses</em> (final clauses expressing the goal of an action), where it is equivalent to Czech/Slovenian <em>aby/da</em>; and (2) <em>different-subject complements</em> of volitional verbs, where the embedded subject is distinct from the matrix subject. In both cases, [w dat :i 3sg] is followed by a finite present-tense verb:</p>
      <tb>
        <r><c>Environment</c><c>Form</c><c>Example</c></r>
        <r><c>purpose (any subject)</c><c>[w dat :i 3sg] + present</c><c><ex>[w on] [w ydat :i 3sg] [w dat :i 3sg] [w kupit :i 3sg] [w vyno]</ex> "he goes to buy wine"</c></r>
        <r><c>different-subject complement</c><c>[w dat :i 3sg] + present</c><c><ex>[w az] [w xotit :i 1sg] [w dat :i 3sg] [w ydat :i 3sg]</ex> "I want him/her to go"</c></r>
      </tb>
      <p>Crucially, [w dat :i 3sg] is <em>not</em> used when the matrix and embedded subjects are the same — the infinitive is used instead. This parallels the function of Czech <em>aby</em> and Slovenian <em>da</em>, which similarly appear in purpose clauses and different-subject complements rather than as general complementizers:</p>
      <list>
        <item><ex>[w az] [w xotit :i 1sg] [w ydat]</ex> "I want to go" (same subject → infinitive, no [w dat :i 3sg])</item>
        <item><ex>[w az] [w xotit :i 1sg] [w dat :i 3sg] [w ydat :i 3sg]</ex> "I want him/her to go" (different subject → [w dat :i 3sg] + present)</item>
        <item><ex>[w on] [st доіл :t doil] [w dat :i 3sg] [w vydit :i 3sg] [w ta] [st краль :t kral]</ex> "he came in order to see the king" (purpose clause)</item>
        <item><ex>[w my] [w možit :i 1pl] [w doit]</ex> "we can come" (same subject → infinitive after modal)</item>
        <item><ex>[w my] [w xotit :i 1pl] [w dat :i 3sg] [w doit :i 3pl] [w ony]</ex> "we want them to come" (different subject → [w dat :i 3sg])</item>
      </list>
      <p>The subject-identity condition is strict: if the embedded predicate has a distinct, overt subject, [w dat :i 3sg] is required; if it shares the matrix subject, [w dat :i 3sg] is ungrammatical and the infinitive is the only option. This contrasts sharply with Macedonian and Bulgarian, where a <em>da</em>-construction has largely or entirely displaced the infinitive even in same-subject contexts (Bulgarian <em>искам да отида</em> "I want to go", lit. "I want that I-go"). Styrian [w dat :i 3sg] has not entered that competition at all: its distribution is grammaticalized on the subject-identity split, not on the infinitive/finite alternation found in Balkan Slavic. BCS represents an intermediate position — <em>da</em> is more widespread than in Slovenian or Czech but has not replaced the infinitive as completely as in Bulgarian/Macedonian — and Styrian aligns with Slovenian rather than with BCS.</p>
      <p><em>Purpose clauses with negation.</em> A negated purpose clause uses [w dat :i 3sg] [w ne] + present ("in order not to, so as not to"). The particle [w dat :i 3sg] remains and [w ne] follows it as a proclitic to the finite verb:</p>
      <list>
        <item><ex>[w on] [w ydat :i 3sg] [st бержо :t berzho] [w dat :i 3sg] [w ne] [st закасне :t zakasne]</ex> "he goes quickly so as not to be late"</item>
        <item><ex>[w az] [st затворем :t zatvorim] [w ta] [st врата :t vrata] [w dat :i 3sg] [w ne] [w ydat :i 3sg] [w studenə]</ex> "I close the door so that the cold doesn't come in"</item>
      </list>
      <p><em>Embedded subject and the clitic cluster.</em> In a [w dat :i 3sg]-clause, [w dat :i 3sg] counts as XP₁ of the embedded clause. The clitic cluster follows it at 2P; the required overt subject of the embedded clause follows the cluster in the standard displaced-subject position. This is the pattern already illustrated under §Embedded Clauses:</p>
      <list>
        <item><ex>[w az] [w xotit :i 1sg] [w dat :i 3sg] [w byt :i 3sg] [w ty] [w on] [w dat :i lptc.m] [w taf] [w knyha]</ex> "I want him to give you the book" — [w dat :i 3sg] as XP₁; cluster [[st е ти :t e ty]]; required subject [w on] displaced after cluster</item>
        <item><ex>[w ony] [w doit :i 3pl] [w dat :i 3sg] [w mu] [w on] [w pokazat :i 3sg] [w ta] [w hrad]</ex> "they are coming so that he can show them the town" — purpose; cluster [[st му :t mu]]; subject [w on] displaced</item>
      </list>
      <p><em>Historical note.</em> The restriction of [w dat :i 3sg] to purpose and different-subject complements reflects a diachronic narrowing. In earlier Styrian, contact with German — which has no <em>da</em>-construction at all — did not directly reshape the distribution of [w dat :i 3sg], but may have reinforced the infinitive in same-subject contexts by providing a structural model (German <em>um zu</em> + infinitive, see §За + Infinitive: Purpose Construction). More decisively, sustained literary and prestige contact with Czech, which uses <em>aby</em> specifically for purpose and different-subject complements, stabilized the same functional distribution in Styrian. The modern pattern therefore represents a convergence point between Czech/Slovenian functional grammar and indigenous Styrian development. The cohortative idiom [w dat :i 3sg] + 1pl present ([w dat :i 3sg] [w pysat :i 1pl]! "let's write!") is a lexicalized relic of an earlier, slightly broader [w dat :i 3sg] and should be treated as fixed rather than as evidence for productive extension of [w dat :i 3sg] into same-subject territory.</p>
      <p>The 1pl cohortative retains [w dat :i 3sg] + 1pl present as a fixed idiom: <ex>[w dat :i 3sg] [w pysat :i 1pl]!</ex> "let's write!" This is lexicalized and does not constitute a productive use of [w dat :i 3sg] with a same-subject complement.</p>
    </sub>
    <sub t="За + Infinitive: Purpose Construction">
      <p>An alternative purpose strategy uses the preposition [w za] followed directly by the infinitive. This construction expresses goal or purpose with the same subject, and is areally motivated by contact with German <em>um zu</em> + infinitive. It competes freely with the [w dat :i 3sg] + present purpose clause, particularly in same-subject contexts:</p>
      <list>
        <item><ex>[w az] [w ydat :i 1sg] [w za] [w kupat] [st хлеба :t xleba]</ex> "I go to buy bread" (lit. "for-to-buy bread")</item>
        <item><ex>[w on] [st вставалӑ :t vstavală] [st рано :t rano] [w za] [w vydit] [w ta] [st сонце :t sonce]</ex> "he got up early in order to see the sun"</item>
        <item><ex>[w my] [w byt :i 1pl] [w tuka] [w za] [w delat]</ex> "we are here to work"</item>
        <item><ex>[w az] [w ymat :i 1sg] [w uše] [st многом :t mnohom] [w za] [w rekat]</ex> "I still have many things to say"</item>
        <item><ex>[w ona] [w doit :i lptc.f] [w za] [w čitat] [w taf :i f.sg.obl] [w knyha :i obl.sg]</ex> "she came to read the book"</item>
        <item><ex>[w on] [w ydat :i lptc.m] [w do] [w dom :i obl.sg] [w za] [w delat]</ex> "he went home to work"</item>
      </list>
      <p>The [w za] + infinitive and [w dat :i 3sg] + finite compete in purpose contexts; the former tends to feel slightly more formal or deliberate, while the latter is more colloquial. Both are grammatically well-formed. The [w za] + infinitive construction is <em>only</em> used for same-subject purpose; it cannot express different-subject complements.</p>
    </sub>
    <p>Other examples of subordination:</p>
    <list>
      <item><ex>[w az] [st знам :t znam] [w dak] [w on] [w byt :i 3sg] [w tuka]</ex> "I know that he is here"</item>
      <item><ex>[w ony] [w doit :i 3pl] [w koga] [w byt :i 3sg] [st готовӑ :t hotovă]</ex> "they will come when it is ready"</item>
      <item><ex>[w my] [w ne] [w možit :i 1pl] [w doit] [w zače] [w nema] [w voda]</ex> "we can't come because there is no water"</item>
      <item><ex><em>[w on] [st пише :t pyše] [st хот :t ħot] [w byt :i 3sg] [st боланӑ :t bolană]</em></ex> "he writes although sick"</item>
    </list>
  </sec>
  <sec t="Conditional Sentences">
    <p>Ordinary real or open conditionals use [w ako] + present/non-past:</p>
    <list>
      <item><ex>[w ako :c] [w ty] [w ymat :i 2sg] [w voda], [w dat] [w my].</ex> "If you have water, give me some."</item>
      <item><ex>[w ako :c] [w ony] [w doit :i 3pl] [w utre], [w my] [w xotit :i 1pl] [w vydit] [w ykh].</ex> "If they come tomorrow, we'd like to see them."</item>
    </list>
    <p>Hypothetical or counterfactual conditionals use [w ako] + past tense in the condition clause and [w by] + the appropriate singular or plural l-participle in the consequence clause:</p>
    <list>
      <item><ex>[w ako :c] [w ty] [w byt :i 2sg] [w doit :i lptc.m] [st пред :t pred], [w az] [w by] [st моглӑ :t mohlă] [w dat] [w ty] [w taf] [w knyha].</ex> "If you had come earlier, I could have given you the book."</item>
      <item><ex>[w ako :c] [w my] [w ymat :i lptc.pl] [st повештӑ :t povaštă] [w voda], [w my] [w by] [st осталі :t ostali] [w ve] [w hora].</ex> "If we had more water, we would have stayed in the mountains."</item>
    </list>
  </sec>
  <sec t="Topic–Comment Structure">
    <p>With its uninflected adjective system, Styrian lends itself naturally to topic-comment structuring, but present-tense nominal and adjectival predicates still retain an overt copula:</p>
    <list>
      <item><ex><em>[w ta :c] [st говорӑ :t hovoră] [st стирски :t styrsky] [w byt :i 3sg] [st простӑ :t prostă] [st по :t po] [st форма :t forma], [st богат :t bohat] [st по :t po] [w slovo].</em></ex> "Styrian speech is simple in form, rich in vocabulary." (topic-comment reading with overt copula)</item>
      <item><ex><em>[st Сей :t Sej] [w čelovek] [w byt :i 3sg] [w lekar].</em></ex> "That person is a doctor." (identifying sentence with overt copula)</item>
      <item><ex><em>[w hora :c] [w byt :i 3sg] [w holemə], [w reka] [w byt :i 3sg] [st простӑ :t prostă].</em></ex> "The mountain is big, the river is plain." (parallel topic-comment with overt copula)</item>
    </list>
  </sec>
  <sec t="Discourse Particles">
    <p>A small set of discourse-level particles modulate the speaker's attitude or information structure:</p>
    <list>
      <item>[w pak] "again; also; on the other hand" (connects and contrasts)</item>
      <item>[w že] emphasizing/assertive particle (unstressed, attached after the element it emphasizes): <ex>[st той :t toj] [w že] [w byt :i 3sg] [w dobrə]</ex> "that is precisely the good one"</item>
      <item>[w mo] hearsay or inference particle (often post-verbal): <ex>[w on] [w mo] [w byt :i 3sg] [w ydat :i lptc.m]</ex> "he is said to have gone / apparently he went"</item>
      <item>[w syhur] "certainly, surely" (manner adverb also used as a sentence-level particle)</item>
      <item>[st але :t ale] "but" (coordinating)</item>
      <item>[st и :t y] "and" (coordinating)</item>
      <item>[w yly] "or" (coordinating)</item>
    </list>
  </sec>
</ch>
